<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cédric Champeau's blog</title>
    <link>http://melix.github.io/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://melix.github.io/blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>JBake Bootstrap Template</description>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 23:49:28 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 23:49:28 +0200</lastBuildDate>

    <item>
      <title>A week fighting a PermGen leak</title>
      <link>http://melix.github.io/blog/2015/08/permgenleak.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/08/permgenleak.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;h1 id=&quot;_a_challenge_at_gradle&quot; class=&quot;sect0&quot;&gt;A challenge at Gradle&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_a_new_job&quot;&gt;A new job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog post after 4 months being a full time employee of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gradle.org&quot;&gt;Gradle Inc.&lt;/a&gt;! I am pretty excited by this job, even though so far it didn&amp;#8217;t give me much time to contribute to &lt;a href=&quot;http://groovy-lang.org&quot;&gt;Apache Groovy&lt;/a&gt; (but we did manage to release 2.4.4 though). One of the reasons I joined the company was because I love technical challenges. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gradle.org&quot;&gt;Gradle&lt;/a&gt; has a lot of them, with an incredible team of smart people working together to make software automation better. This week, I worked on my first true challenge, and I must confess that I miserably failed :-) This is a long post, and anyone who ever fought against the infamous &quot;PermGen space error&quot; in their application is going to understand why&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_codenarc_as_the_source_of_a_leak&quot;&gt;CodeNarc as the source of a leak?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first suspicious piece of code that draw our attention was &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt;. CodeNarc is a source code quality analysis tool for Groovy, which is used by a lot of Groovy developers, including in Gradle itself (since Gradle intensively makes use of Groovy). &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; can be seen as the equivalent of FindBugs for Groovy code. And problems seemed to start with an upgrade of the Gradle CodeNarc plugin to use CodeNarc 0.23. We actually saw reports like &lt;a href=&quot;https://discuss.gradle.org/t/codenarc-performance-drop-after-versions-update/9677&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; in the forums or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CodeNarc/CodeNarc/issues/116&quot;&gt;this other one&lt;/a&gt; in GitHub but thought that the PermGen error was just a consequence of &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; including more rules: rules are written in Groovy, so compiled down to classes and classes eat PermGen. So increasing the PermGen space was enough, and it did actually solve the error. Problem solved. Or not. The riddle only started for me with a seemingly insignificant question on our internal mailing lists: &quot;Can some investigate why our build sometimes fails with a PermGen space error?&quot;, and I volunteered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I had just finished pushing an upgrade of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gradle.org&quot;&gt;Gradle&lt;/a&gt; to Groovy 2.4.4 on our master branch, and I had noticed that I had to increase the PermGen space too. At first, I naively thought that it was also required because Groovy 2.4 consumed more memory, but I was wrong. I should have known, because before joining Gradle, I had actually worked on Groovy for Android, and a consequence of this work was that Groovy 2.4 had a reduced memory footprint: we generate less bytecode, which directly relates to a reduced PermGen space usage. So why on earth would Groovy 2.4 require more memory? And what is the relation with the CodeNarc plugin? Actually this plugin works in a Gradle version that uses Groovy 2.3.10, so why would there be a relation between the two?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such a case, your best friend is a profiler. But as I will explain here, it can also lead you to wrong tracks. Be careful. The second best friend is the JVM options &lt;code&gt;-XX:+TraceClassLoading&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;+XX:+TraceClassUnloading&lt;/code&gt;. I also used &lt;code&gt;-XX:SoftRefLRUPolicyMSPerMB=0&lt;/code&gt;, an option that I had no idea it existed before my friend David Gageot told me. Basically, it will force the garbage collector to agressively collect all soft references, which is very useful to understand, in combination with the 2 other options, from which classloader we are leaking memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first wrong track was actually thinking that &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; was the source of the problem. I &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/d/topic/gradle-dev/w9F0PsCfI4Y/discussion&quot;&gt;wrote an email on the gradle-dev list&lt;/a&gt;, explaining my findings, and I had indeed found a lot of classes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; were not unloaded. Before I go further, let&amp;#8217;s explain how the JVM is supposed to behave with regards to classes in Java 7. We all know that objects are garbage collected, but for a lot of people, classes are not. That&amp;#8217;s why we have the PermGen space (which has disappeared in Java 8 but that&amp;#8217;s another story): this segregated space of the JVM memory is used to store classes. And in Java, a class is loaded by a classloader. There is a strong reference between a class and its classloader. But what the JVM is able to do is actually simple: if there&amp;#8217;s no instance of the class which is strongly reachable &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; that the classloader is neither strongly reachable, then both the class and the classloader can be unloaded. This means that PermGen can be recovered, and it is pretty useful, especially for a language like Groovy which can generate a lot of classes at runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Gradle, and particularily in the Gradle CodeNarc plugin, &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; is executed through an Ant task, which spawns its own isolated classloader, containing both the &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; and Groovy classes. So when the plugin execution is finished, if we do not keep track of the classloader, classes should be garbage collected. So a good candidate for the memory leak was actually the &lt;code&gt;IsolatedAntBuilder&lt;/code&gt; that Gradle uses to execute the Ant task. And guess what? There is such a leak, because the &lt;code&gt;DefaultIsolatedAntBuilder&lt;/code&gt; performs classloader caching! That was also discovered by my colleague Sterling, who immediately spot that: while we do cache the classloaders, keeping a strong reference on them, we don&amp;#8217;t have any code to release the classloader in case of memory pressure. Conclusion, we&amp;#8217;ve found the memory leak, hurray! And it has nothing to do with &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://groovy-lang.org&quot;&gt;Apache Groovy&lt;/a&gt;, pfiew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I immediately tried to disable the cache, which turned to be pretty trivial. Run the build again and&amp;#8230; another PermGen space error. No CodeNarc classes unloaded, no Groovy classes unloaded. Wow. So the problem wasn&amp;#8217;t solved, first &quot;oh my!&quot; moment of the week: there was &lt;strong&gt;another&lt;/strong&gt; leak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One test I did, then, is to totally comment out the code that, in the ant builder code, performed the definition of the CodeNarc task. Eventually, there was only that code left in the CodeNarc plugin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    @TaskAction
    void run() {
        logging.captureStandardOutput(LogLevel.INFO)
        def classpath = new DefaultClassPath(getCodenarcClasspath())
        antBuilder.withClasspath(classpath.asFiles).execute {
            // ... thou shalt not leak!
        }
    }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I executed the code again, and there was definitely a leak: after several loops, a PermGen error occurred. &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; was ruled out as the source of the leak. After some hours of trials, study of memory snapshots, I eventually came out with a piece of code that reproduces the problem independently of Gradle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;int i = 0;
try {
    while (true) {
        i++;
	URLClassLoader loader = new URLClassLoader(
            new URL[]{new File(GROOVY_JAR).toURI().toURL()},
            ClassLoader.getSystemClassLoader().getParent());
        Class system = loader.loadClass(&quot;groovy.lang.GroovySystem&quot;);
        system.getDeclaredMethod(&quot;getMetaClassRegistry&quot;).invoke(null);
        loader.close();
    }
} catch (OutOfMemoryError e) {
    System.err.println(&quot;Failed after &quot; + i + &quot; loadings&quot;);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the code is very simple: it creates a new isolated classloader, which only contains Groovy on classpath. Then it invokes the creation of the Groovy runtime, by asking the metaclass registry, then it closes the classloader. On my JVM, after about 40 runs, the code fails with a PermGen space error: despite the fact that no class, no object is kept out of the classloader, the Groovy runtime is not unloaded, leading to a memory leak. The key point here is that I had noticed some oddities during my hours of debugging: a class, named &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;, was at the center of those oddities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;imageblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://groups.google.com/group/gradle-dev/attach/cb238029e9b0/leak.png?part=0.1&amp;authuser=0&quot; alt=&quot;ClassInfo leak&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, although &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourkit.com/features/&quot;&gt;YourKit&lt;/a&gt; (the profiler I was using) was telling me that all classes, all classloaders were weakly or softly reachable (btw, it&amp;#8217;s really a pity that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourkit.com/features/&quot;&gt;YourKit&lt;/a&gt; doesn&amp;#8217;t show them separately, that is, weakly referenced objects from softly referenced ones), the classes were not garbage collected. Also strangely, some classes appeared as GC roots, meaning they could be collected, but they weren&amp;#8217;t! And when I navigated through some of the duplicate classes I was seeing, &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; was present, as a value of a map entry of class value. Here we are, I had found the real source of the leak. Something had changed in Groovy. And the fact that &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; was leaking since 0.23 was just a side effect of upgrading its dependency to Groovy 2.4! So despite Gradle was using Groovy 2.3.10, CodeNarc, by default, was using a more recent version of Groovy. That doesn&amp;#8217;t explain &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; it leaks yet, but we now know who is responsible: Groovy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_classvalue_friend_or_foe&quot;&gt;ClassValue, friend or foe?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Groovy 2.4, Groovy uses a new mechanism for storing its runtime metadata in case you run on JDK 7 or later: &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; allows storing information on the class level. Typically, a language like Groovy would use it to store the metaclass of a class. In practice, Groovy doesn&amp;#8217;t directly store the metaclass here, but a higher level concept called &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;, which in turns gives access to the metaclass of a class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Groovy 2.4, all that information was stored directly in the &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; class itself, through a private static field. &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; is therefore the global entry point for accessing runtime information about a class. While Groovy 2.4 still uses &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; as an entry point, there are 2 possible storage mechanisms, based on the underlying JDK. If &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; is available; which is the case for any JDK 7+, then it is used, otherwise we fallback on the old mechanism. &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; is supposed to be more efficient and more direct. Of course, in any case (old and new storage mechanism), it is memory sensitive: in case a class is not available anymore, its &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; is removed. What &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; storage provides is basically the same as ThreadLocal, but at the Class level instead of the Thread level. Users are allowed to store information here, but one should be aware that as thread locals, if you start using it, you may face memory leaks if you don&amp;#8217;t use it properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s for the theory, let&amp;#8217;s see how in practice this change led to a giant memory leak in the Gradle build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory is that &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; should behave like ThreadLocal. That is, the entries stored in the internal map of the Class class, should be garbage collected when the referent is not strongly referenced anymore. This behavior is however not what the JVM does. It was confirmed to me by Charles Nutter (JRuby) a few hours later: although we all expected the JVM to collect the unreachable, it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/iNikem&quot;&gt;@inikem&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CedricChampeau&quot;&gt;@cedricchampeau&lt;/a&gt; I talked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/haupz&quot;&gt;@haupz&lt;/a&gt; at JVMLS and he agrees that ClassValue *should* work like ThreadLocal wrt dereferencing.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Charles Nutter (@headius) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/headius/status/636910965817143297&quot;&gt;27 Août 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uh. Second &quot;oh my!&quot; moment of the weak. I had now a candidate (Groovy) and a reason (&lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; leaking). However, it doesn&amp;#8217;t explain by itself why the class loader is not garbage collected: if Groovy stores information on classes, it&amp;#8217;s ok, as long as the classes to which it writes some metadata are from the classloader, or any child classloader, of the Groovy runtime itself. Everything would be self-contained, meaning we would have a graph of objects that do not leak outside of the isolated classloader. However&amp;#8230; Groovy uses Strings, integers, List, &amp;#8230; all coming from the system classloader. And that is the main difference with the old metadata storage mechanism: the old one only &lt;strong&gt;referenced&lt;/strong&gt; classes from the system classloader. With &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt;, we are &lt;strong&gt;modifying&lt;/strong&gt; classes from the system classloader too! That is, the String class, for example, contains in its class value map, information from the Groovy runtime! The famous &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; instance is present there! There we are! We leaked a &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; instance into the system classloader! So what happens is that when we are done with our &quot;isolated&quot; Groovy runtime, we think it should unload because nothing references any object or class from that classloader. However, the Groovy runtime did update classes from the system classloader, and it started leaking into it! The ghost in the shell! Groovy is spoiling everywhere&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far so good, I had the explanation, I could write a workaround: let&amp;#8217;s iterate over all those classes that Groovy updated, remove the &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;, and we&amp;#8217;re done. I wrote that code, and it turned out to be a bit ugly, but&amp;#8230; it worked! Here is, for information, the cleanup code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    static void removeClassFromGlobalClassSet(Class&amp;lt;?&amp;gt; classInfoClass) throws Exception {
        Field globalClassValueField = classInfoClass.getDeclaredField(&quot;globalClassValue&quot;);
        globalClassValueField.setAccessible(true);
        Object globalClassValue = globalClassValueField.get(null);
        Method removeFromGlobalClassValue = globalClassValueField.getType().getDeclaredMethod(&quot;remove&quot;, Class.class);
        removeFromGlobalClassValue.setAccessible(true);

        Field globalClassSetField = classInfoClass.getDeclaredField(&quot;globalClassSet&quot;);
        globalClassSetField.setAccessible(true);
        Object globalClassSet = globalClassSetField.get(null);
        globalClassSetField = globalClassSet.getClass().getDeclaredField(&quot;items&quot;);
        globalClassSetField.setAccessible(true);
        Object globalClassSetItems = globalClassSetField.get(globalClassSet);

        Field clazzField = classInfoClass.getDeclaredField(&quot;klazz&quot;);
        clazzField.setAccessible(true);


        Iterator it = (Iterator) globalClassSetItems.getClass().getDeclaredMethod(&quot;iterator&quot;).invoke(globalClassSetItems);

        while (it.hasNext()) {
            Object classInfo = it.next();
            Object clazz = clazzField.get(`ClassInfo`);
            removeFromGlobalClassValue.invoke(globalClassValue, clazz);
        }

    }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After executing that code, no &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; instance was leaking anymore into the system classloader, and the runtime could be shutdown properly. The garbage collector did its job, and yay! I&amp;#8217;m so happy, I&amp;#8217;ll be able to sleep soon! That was tuesday night. And that night, I thought I had found the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_memory_sensitive_classloader_caching&quot;&gt;Memory sensitive classloader caching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So wednesday, I spent the day trying to implement the same strategy inside Gradle. More precisely, inside the &lt;code&gt;IsolatedAntBuilder&lt;/code&gt; thing I told you. I implemented the code, launched my test again and hurray! it worked! My test passed! No more PermGen space error! So all I had to do, now, was to reactivate classloader caching, otherwise, we would loose a feature that is important performance wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I reactivated the cache, and boom! That time, the Gradle build did &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; fail with a PermGen error, but with very strange errors like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;groovy.lang.MissingMethodException: No signature of method: java.lang.Integer.plus() is applicable for argument types: (java.lang.Integer) values: [0]
&amp;gt;  Possible solutions: plus(java.lang.String), plus(java.lang.Character), abs(), use([Ljava.lang.Object;), split(groovy.lang.Closure), minus(java.lang.Character)&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mmmmmm&amp;#8230; 3rd &quot;oh my!&quot; moment of the week. I understood what I had just done. By clearing the &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; stuff from the classloader, I had effectively shutdown the Groovy runtime that was initiated in that cached classloader. So when some code was trying to reuse the runtime from that cached classloader, since I had disabled it, it was failing! And there&amp;#8217;s no option to reinitialize the Groovy runtime. It&amp;#8217;s just not doable, because everything happens in static initializers (private final fields, &amp;#8230;). So unless the JVM had an option to allow to re-execute the static initializers of a class (and who knows what oddities it would lead to), I had no luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s about when I told my mates at Gradle &quot;I think we have to choose between caching and leaking memory&quot;. But the night came, and I actually had an idea. I could implement a memory sensitive cache: by writing a smart cache structure with appropriate SoftReferences and reference queues, I would be able to execute the shutdown code only when I know that the GC is trying to reclaim memory. The idea is simple: we have a map, which key is a SoftRefence&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;, and the value is our cached classloader. The Sterling represents the classpath that we are caching for the classloader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that the GC is out of memory. The semantics of SoftReference are clear: before throwing an OutOfMemoryError, the JVM will do its best and clear all soft references. Doing so, using a custom reference queue, we can be notified that the reference is cleared. Then, we can execute the Groovy runtime shutdown code, which will in turn make the ClassLoader collectible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly I was pretty happy with my implementation. I executed the code and it worked! Caching was working until the GC tried to reclaim memory, then I saw my shutdow code executed, memory reclaimed and green tests. Woooo!!! I had eventually knocked that memory leak down! Ha ha!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I remembered that my colleague Sterling had a test which involved a loop in an integration test. To make sure I had &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; fixed the leak, I asked him to tell me how he did that. The code was very simple, just involving a loop thanks to &lt;code&gt;@Unroll&lt;/code&gt; in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spockframework.org&quot;&gt;Spock specification&lt;/a&gt;. I did it and&amp;#8230; PermGen error showed up again. WAT?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the fourth &quot;oh my!&quot; moment. And not the last one. I really then spent hours in modifying my caching code, refactored my code to add more complicated memory leak strategies, seeing that there were still thread locals, clearing them explicitly, adding a memory leak strategy for Ant itself, for the Java Beans introspector, &amp;#8230; None of my attempts worked. In the end, it always failed. But there was always one mystery: I saw that the Groovy classes were unloading. But the Ant classes were not&amp;#8230; And the rest, I should have discovered that much sooner. But when you have so many potential source leaks, that are much more evident, it&amp;#8217;s so hard to figure out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, one thing would have made things much easier to discover. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourkit.com/features/&quot;&gt;YourKit&lt;/a&gt;, you can see that there are duplicate classes. Classes that have the same name, but come from different class loaders. However, there&amp;#8217;s nothing that will &lt;strong&gt;show&lt;/strong&gt; you those duplicates. You have to find them yourself. And in the end, when in the dump you see an instance of that class, all you can see is that it is an instance of &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;. Nothing, visually, tells you that the instance of &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; that you are seeing actually comes from a different classloader from the one you are seeing just next to it. A bit of color, for example, would help&amp;#8230;. And it would have helped me seeing that some &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; elements that I was seeing in the classes from Ant didn&amp;#8217;t come from the &quot;disposable&quot; Groovy runtime&amp;#8230; No. They were coming from&amp;#8230; the Gradle runtime itself!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_where_it_all_ends&quot;&gt;Where it all ends&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, That was the last &quot;oh my!&quot; moment of the week. The one that killed all my hopes. And to understand the problem, I now have to explain to you how &lt;code&gt;IsolatedAntBuilder&lt;/code&gt; works. It&amp;#8217;s a very small, yet very smart and practical piece of code. Maybe too smart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradle, as a core feature, lets you execute Ant tasks thanks to code inherited from the Groovy codebase itself: AntBuilder. It&amp;#8217;s a very elegant piece of code, that lets you write things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;task check &amp;lt;&amp;lt; {
    ant.taskdef(name: &apos;pmd&apos;,
                classname: &apos;net.sourceforge.pmd.ant.PMDTask&apos;,
                classpath: configurations.pmd.asPath)
    ant.pmd(shortFilenames: &apos;true&apos;,
            failonruleviolation: &apos;true&apos;,
            rulesetfiles: file(&apos;pmd-rules.xml&apos;).toURI().toString()) {
        formatter(type: &apos;text&apos;, toConsole: &apos;true&apos;)
        fileset(dir: &apos;src&apos;)
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this works, there&amp;#8217;s actually a lot involved behind that. Including classloader magic. In particular, in the example above, we create a task definition in Ant, which uses a classpath defined in Gradle. &quot;ant&quot; here is a global object which is shared accross the build, but it is possible to avoid the classes from the Ant tasks to be mixed with the Gradle classpath itself by using antBuilder instead. That&amp;#8217;s what the &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; plugin does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;antBuilder.withClasspath(classpath.asFiles).execute {
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;means &quot;Gradle, please, create an isolated classloader for me, that will contain the classpath only necessary for CodeNarc, and execute that Ant task with it&quot;. It seems very trivial, but there is a problem. The code that you see here is found in a Gradle script. It means that the &quot;antBuilder&quot; object that you are seeing here comes from Gradle. It is our &lt;code&gt;IsolatedAntBuilder&lt;/code&gt; instance. When we call &quot;withClasspath&quot;, a new instance of &lt;code&gt;IsolatedAntBuilder&lt;/code&gt; will be created, with an isolated classloader corresponding to the supplied classpath. Then calling execute with a closure that lets you configure the ant task using the Groovy AntBuilder syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the &quot;Closure&quot; class that we are seeing here comes from Gradle. Then, we have a classloader which contains the Ant runtime, and a &quot;bridge&quot; class, written in Groovy, called &quot;AntBuilderDelegate&quot;, which has one responsibility: when the code of the Ant builder is going to be executed, it is likely that the version of Groovy which will be found on classpath will be &lt;strong&gt;different&lt;/strong&gt; from the one that Gradle uses. That is exactly what happens with &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt;: Gradle 2.6 uses Groovy 2.3.10, but the &lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; plugin executes with Groovy 2.4.1, so the Ant task works with a different &quot;Closure&quot; class than the one that Gradle has. We will really have two distinct &quot;Closure&quot; classes here, and &quot;AntBuilderDelegate&quot; is responsible for filling the gap: when the Ant configuration code, which will use AntBuilder from the Ant classpath, is going to be executed, it will be calling AntBuilderDelegate instead of directly the Closure code. And that code will intercept the missing methods in order to &quot;reroute&quot; them to the builder. You don&amp;#8217;t have to understand that in detail, it&amp;#8217;s not really the point here, but it is important to understand that this &quot;AntBuilderDelegate&quot; class is instantiated&amp;#8230; in Gradle, using the Gradle classloader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you may see it coming. I told you I had upgraded Gradle to use Groovy 2.4.4. So what does it mean? Gradle now uses Groovy with &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt;. And what is the problem with &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt;? All classes &quot;touched&quot; by Groovy will have them &quot;polluted&quot; with necessary metadata information. So when we create an instance of &quot;AntBuilderDelegate&quot;, we&amp;#8217;re doing that using the Groovy 2.4 runtime from Gradle, which comes with its own &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;. And that delegate references and AntBuilder which is instantiated using the Ant classloader, with a different Groovy runtime, having its own &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;. So what I had found earlier was that the &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; from the Groovy &quot;Ant&quot; runtime was leaking into Gradle. But I hadn&amp;#8217;t realized that the opposite was also true! By bridging the runtimes, we were leaking Groovy &quot;Gradle&quot; into the isolated classloader, through &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what happened, is that the Groovy classes from the isolated classpath were garbage collected, because no &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; from Gradle leaked into them. However, the Ant classes were touched. And they were NOT collectible then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is were I stopped. Because if I found a way to &quot;unload&quot; &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; from the isolated classpath and the touched classes from the system classloader, I haven&amp;#8217;t found a way to do the same for the &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; instances that leak into the Ant runtime&amp;#8230; Of course I tried a &quot;brute force&quot; thing, by removing all &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt; from those classes, but as you understood, it&amp;#8217;s a desperate attempt: it&amp;#8217;s equivalent to shutting down the runtime. And then, it totally breaks subsequent calls in the Gradle build, we&amp;#8217;ve just broken the Groovy runtime from Gradle&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s were I felt desperate. After a week fighting those memory leaks, and so many &quot;ah ah, got you!&quot; moments, I was in front of a wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_what_s_next&quot;&gt;What&amp;#8217;s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do next? One has to remember that fixing Groovy is not the ultimate solution because Gradle uses Groovy internally, but the various tasks can very well use a different Groovy version which is beyond our control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rollback Groovy in Gradle to use Groovy 2.3.10. It would avoid the Groovy classes from Gradle to leak into the Isolated classloaders, but is also unfortunate given the improvements that this version provides. Also, those who write Groovy applications for Android use Groovy 2.4+&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codenarc.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;CodeNarc&lt;/a&gt; would still use Groovy 2.4+, we could downgrade it too. However, if people rely on features of Groovy 2.4+, they just have no choice, so we would still have the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use smarter techniques like instrumentation to track the leakages of &lt;code&gt;ClassInfo&lt;/code&gt;, record them, and revert when we&amp;#8217;re done. It&amp;#8217;s doable, but it&amp;#8217;s a huge amount of work, and relying on instrumentation for Gradle would be very bad for performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update Gradle to use FilteringClassLoader everywhere, including in its main process, to prevent &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; to be found. This would work because without that class, Groovy wouldn&amp;#8217;t use &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt; to store the metadata and fall back to the old mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait for a fix in Groovy. Jochen is already working on that, but we know that the old mechanism isn&amp;#8217;t perfect either, and has memory leaks too. That was one of the reasons to migrate to &lt;code&gt;ClassValue&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait for a fix of the JVM. That&amp;#8217;s beyond our control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increase the PermGen space for builds that use the code quality plugins, which internally use AntBuilder. It&amp;#8217;s what we do today. It works, but it&amp;#8217;s just hiding the problem. And we have to explain to our users to do it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some smart people come with a smart solution, that&amp;#8217;s why I wrote this too. During that week, I got help from lots of people, including Jochen &quot;Groovy&quot; Theodorou, Henri &quot;EasyMock&quot; Tremblay, David Gageot or Nikita Salnikov from Plumbr, thank you guys!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you wonder, the same problem exist in JDK 8 too, it&amp;#8217;s just not visible immediately because of the metaspace that appeared to replace the PermGen space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it was fun writing this &quot;post-mortem&quot;, I hope it wasn&amp;#8217;t too obscure, it helped me a lot because I had so many &quot;got it&quot; and &quot;oh noes!&quot; moments that I felt it was very interesting to share this story with you. And if you like technical challenges, do not forget that &lt;a href=&quot;https://gradle.org/gradle-jobs/&quot;&gt;Gradle is hiring&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved sandboxing of Groovy scripts</title>
      <link>http://melix.github.io/blog/2015/03/sandboxing.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/03/sandboxing.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;div id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most current uses cases of Groovy is scripting. Groovy makes it very easy to execute code dynamically, at runtime. Depending
on the application, scripts can be found in multiple sources: file system, databases, remote services, &amp;#8230; but more importantly, the
designer of the application which executes scripts is not necessarily the one writing those scripts. Moreover, the scripts might run in a
constrained environment (limited memory, file descriptors, time, &amp;#8230;) or your you simply don&amp;#8217;t want to allow users to access the full
capabilities of the language from a script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;openblock INFO&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;What you will learn in this post&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;why Groovy is a good fit to write internal DSLs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what it implies in terms of security in your applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;how you can customize compilation to improve the DSL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the meaning of &lt;code&gt;SecureASTCustomizer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what are type checking extensions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;how you can rely on type checking extensions to offer proper sandboxing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, imagine that you want to offer users the ability to evaluate mathematical expressions. One option would be to implement your
own internal DSL, create a parser and eventually an interpreter for those expressions. Obviously this involves a bit of work, but if in
the end you need to improve performance, for example by generating bytecode for the expressions instead of evaluating them, or introduce
caching of those runtime generated classes, then Groovy is probably a very good option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of options available, described in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/index.html#_integrating_groovy_in_a_java_application&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;
but the most simple example is just using the &lt;code&gt;Eval&lt;/code&gt; class:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Example.java&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;int sum = (Integer) Eval.me(&quot;1+1&quot;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code &lt;code&gt;1+1&lt;/code&gt; is parsed, compiled to bytecode, loaded and eventually executed by Groovy at runtime. Of course in this example the code is very simple, and you will want to
add parameters, but the idea is that the code which is executed here is arbitrary. This is probably not what you want. For a calculator, you want to allow expressions like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1+1
x+y
1+(2*x)**y
cos(alpha)*r
v=1+x&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but certainly not&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;println &apos;Hello&apos;
(0..100).each { println &apos;Blah&apos; }
Pong p = new Pong()
println(new File(&apos;/etc/passwd&apos;).text)
System.exit(-1)
Eval.me(&apos;System.exit(-1)&apos;) // a script within a script!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where things start to become complicated, and where we start seeing actually multiple needs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;restricting the grammar of the language to a subset of its capabilities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;preventing users from executing unexpected code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;preventing users from executing malicious code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calculator example is pretty simple, but for more complex DSLs, people might actually start writing problematic code without noticing, especially if the DSL is suffiently elegant to be used
by &lt;em&gt;non developers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in this situation a few years ago, when I designed an engine that used Groovy &quot;scripts&quot; written by linguists. One of the problems was that they could unintentionally create infinite loops,
for example. Code was executing on the server, and then you had a thread eating 100% of the CPU and had no choice but restart the application server so I had to find a way to mitigate that
problem without compromising the DSL nor the tooling or the performance of the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, lots of people have similar needs. During the past 4 years, I spoke to tons of users who had a similar question: &lt;em&gt;How can I prevent users from doing bad things in Groovy scripts?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_compilation_customizers&quot;&gt;Compilation customizers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, I had implemented my own solution, but I knew that other people also had implemented similar ones. In the end, Guillaume Laforge
suggested to me that I wrote something that would help fixing those issues and make into Groovy core. This happened in Groovy 1.8.0 with
&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/index.html#compilation-customizers&quot;&gt;compilation customizers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compilation customizers are a set of classes that are aimed at tweaking the compilation of Groovy scripts. You can write your own customizer but Groovy ships with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;an import customizer, which aims at adding imports transparently to scripts, so that users do not have to add &quot;import&quot; statements&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;an AST (Abstract Syntax Tree) transformation customizer, which allows to add AST transformations transparently to scripts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a secure AST customizer, which aims at restricting the grammar and syntactical constructs of the language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AST transformation customizer allowed me to solve the infinite loop issue, by applying the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/gapi/groovy/transform/ThreadInterrupt.html&quot;&gt;@ThreadInterrupt&lt;/a&gt;
transformation, but the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/api/org/codehaus/groovy/control/customizers/SecureASTCustomizer.html&quot;&gt;SecureASTCustomizer&lt;/a&gt; is probably the one which has
been the most misinterpreted of the whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must apologize for this. Back then, I had no better name in mind. The important part of SecureASTCustomizer is &lt;strong&gt;AST&lt;/strong&gt;. It was aimed at restricting access to some features of the AST. The
&quot;secure&quot; part is actually not a good name at all, and I will illustrate why. You can even find a blog post from Kohsuke Kawagushi, of Jenkins fame, named
Groovy SecureASTCustomizer is harmful[&lt;a href=&quot;http://kohsuke.org/2012/04/27/groovy-secureastcustomizer-is-harmful/&quot;&gt;http://kohsuke.org/2012/04/27/groovy-secureastcustomizer-is-harmful/&lt;/a&gt;]. It is very true. The SecureASTCustomizer has never been designed with sandboxing
in mind. It was designed to restrict the language at compile time, not runtime. So a much better name, in retrospect, would have been &lt;em&gt;GrammarCustomizer&lt;/em&gt;. But as you&amp;#8217;re certainly aware, there
are two hard things in computer science: cache invalidation, naming things and off by one errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So imagine that you think of the secure AST customizer as a way of securing your script, and that you want to use this to prevent a user from calling &lt;code&gt;System.exit&lt;/code&gt; from a script. The
documentation says that you can prevent calls on some specific receivers by defining either a blacklist or a whitelist. In terms of securing something, I would always recommand to use a
whitelist, that is to say to list explicitly what is allowed, rather than a blacklist, saying what is disallowed. The reason is that hackers always think of things you don&amp;#8217;t, so let&amp;#8217;s illustrate
this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how a naive &quot;sandbox&quot; script engine could be configured using the &lt;code&gt;SecureASTCustomizer&lt;/code&gt;. I am writing the examples of configuration in Java, even though I could write them in Groovy, just
to make the difference between the integration code and the scripts clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class Sandbox {
    public static void main(String[] args)  {
        CompilerConfiguration conf = new CompilerConfiguration();				&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;
        SecureASTCustomizer customizer = new SecureASTCustomizer();				&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
        customizer.setReceiversBlackList(Arrays.asList(System.class.getName()));		&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
        conf.addCompilationCustomizers(customizer);						&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(4)&lt;/b&gt;
        GroovyShell shell = new GroovyShell(conf);						&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(5)&lt;/b&gt;
        Object v = shell.evaluate(&quot;System.exit(-1)&quot;);						&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(6)&lt;/b&gt;
        System.out.println(&quot;Result = &quot; +v);							&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(7)&lt;/b&gt;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;create a compiler configuration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;create a secure AST customizer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;declare that the &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; class is blacklisted as the receiver of method calls&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;add the customizer to the compiler configuration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;associate the configuration to the script shell, that is, try to create a sandbox&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;6&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;execute a nasty script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;7&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;print the result of the execution of the script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you run this class, when the script is executed, it will throw an error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;General error during canonicalization: Method calls not allowed on [java.lang.System]
java.lang.SecurityException: Method calls not allowed on [java.lang.System]&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the result of the application of the secure AST customizer, which prevents the execution of methods on the &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; class. Success! Now we have secured our script! Oh wait&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_secureastcustomizer_pwned&quot;&gt;SecureASTCustomizer pwned!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secure you say? So what if I do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def c = System
c.exit(-1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execute again and you will see that the program exits &lt;strong&gt;without&lt;/strong&gt; error and &lt;strong&gt;without&lt;/strong&gt; printing the result. The return code of the process is -1, which indicates that the user script has been executed!
What happened? Basically, at compile time, the secure AST customizer is not able to recognize that &lt;code&gt;c.exit&lt;/code&gt; is a call on &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt;, because it works at the AST level! It analyzes a method call, and
in this case the method call is &lt;code&gt;c.exit(-1)&lt;/code&gt;, then gets the receiver and checks if the receiver is in the whitelist (or blacklist). In this case, the receiver is &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; and this variable is &lt;strong&gt;declared
with def&lt;/strong&gt;, which is equivalent to declaring it as &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;, so it will think that &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually there are &lt;strong&gt;many&lt;/strong&gt; ways to workaround the various configurations that you can make on the secure AST customizer. Just for fun, a few of them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;((Object)System).exit(-1)
Class.forName(&apos;java.lang.System&apos;).exit(-1)
(&apos;java.lang.System&apos; as Class).exit(-1)

import static java.lang.System.exit
exit(-1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and there are &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; more options. The dynamic nature of Groovy just makes it impossible to resolve those cases at compile time. There are solutions though. One option is to rely on the JVM standard
security manager. However this is a system wide solution which is often considered as a hammer. But it also doesn&amp;#8217;t really work for all cases, for example you might not want to prevent creation of
files, but only reads for example&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This limitation - or should I say frustration for lots of us - led several people to create a solution based on &lt;strong&gt;runtime checks&lt;/strong&gt;. Runtime checks do not suffer the same problem, because you
will have for example the actual receiver type of a message before checking if a method call is allowed or not. In particular, those implementations are of particular interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jimwhite/Gondor/blob/master/src/org/ifcx/gondor/SecuredScript.java&quot;&gt;SecureScript&lt;/a&gt; by Jim White&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://groovy-sandbox.kohsuke.org/&quot;&gt;Groovy Sandbox&lt;/a&gt; by Kohsuke Kawagushi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/simon-temple/groovy-sandbox&quot;&gt;Groovy Sandbox&lt;/a&gt; by Simon Temple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However none of those implementations is totally secure or reliable. For example, the version by Kohsuke relies on hacking the internal implementation of call site caching. The problem is that it is
not compatible with the invokedynamic version of Groovy, and those internal classes are going to be removed in future versions of Groovy. The version by Simon, on the other hand, relies on AST transformations
but misses a lot of possible hacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, with friends of mine Corinne Krych, Fabrice Matrat and Sébastien Blanc, we decided to create a new runtime sandboxing mechanism that would not have the issues of those projects. We started
implementing this during a hackathon in Nice, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://greachconf.com/speakers/fabrice-matrat-cedric-champeau-groovy-head-in-the-cloud/&quot;&gt;we gave a talk about this last year&lt;/a&gt; at the Greach conference.
It relies on AST transformations and heavily rewrites the code in order to perform a check before each method call, property access, increment of variable, binary expression, &amp;#8230;
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rivieragug/groovy-core/tree/secureruntime&quot;&gt;implementation&lt;/a&gt; is still incomplete, and not much work has been done because I realized there was still a problem in case
of methods or properties called on &quot;implicit this&quot;, like in builders for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xml {
   cars {				 // cars is a method call on an implicit this: &quot;this&quot;.cars(...)
     car(make:&apos;Renault&apos;, model: &apos;Clio&apos;)
   }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of today I still didn&amp;#8217;t find a way to properly handle this because of the design of the meta-object protocol in Groovy, that here relies on the fact that a receiver throws an exception when the method
is not found before trying another receiver. In short, it means that you cannot know the type of the receiver before the method is actually called. And if it is called, it&amp;#8217;s already too late&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until earlier this year I had still no perfect solution to this problem, in case the script being executed is using the dynamic features of the language. But now has come the time to explain how you can
significantly improve the situation if you are ready to loose some of the dynamism of the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_type_checking&quot;&gt;Type checking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s come back to the root problem of the SecureASTCustomizer: it works on the abstract syntax tree and has no knowledge of the concrete types of the receivers of messages. But since Groovy 2, Groovy has
optional compilation, and in Groovy 2.1, we added &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/#_type_checking_extensions&quot;&gt;type checking extensions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type checking extensions are very powerful: they allow the designer of a Groovy DSL to help the compiler infer types, but it also lets you throw compilation errors when normally it should not. Type
checking extensions are even used internally in Groovy to support the static compiler, for example to implement traits or the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/markup-template-engine.html&quot;&gt;markup template engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if, instead of relying on the information available after parsing, we could rely on information from the type checker? Take the following code that our hacker tried to write:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;((Object)System).exit(-1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you activate type checking, this code would not compile:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;1 compilation error:

[Static type checking] - Cannot find matching method java.lang.Object#exit(java.lang.Integer). Please check if the declared type is right and if the method exists.&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this code would not compile anymore. But what if the code is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def c = System
c.exit(-1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can verify that this passes type checking by wrapping the code into a method and running the script with the &lt;code&gt;groovy&lt;/code&gt; command line tool:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@groovy.transform.TypeChecked // or even @CompileStatic
void foo() {
  def c = System
  c.exit(-1)
}
foo()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the type checker will recognize that the &lt;code&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt; method is called on the &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; class and is valid. It will not help us there. But what we know, if this code passes type checking, is that the
compiler recognized the call on the &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; receiver. The idea, then, is to rely on a type checking extension to disallow the call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_a_simple_type_checking_extension&quot;&gt;A simple type checking extension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dig into the details about sandboxing, let&amp;#8217;s try to &quot;secure&quot; our script using a traditional type checking extension. Registering a type checking extension is easy: just set the &lt;code&gt;extensions&lt;/code&gt;
parameter of the &lt;code&gt;@TypeChecked&lt;/code&gt; annotation (or &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic&lt;/code&gt; if you want to use static compilation):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@TypeChecked(extensions=[&apos;SecureExtension1.groovy&apos;])
void foo() {
  def c = System
  c.exit(-1)
}
foo()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extension will be searched on classpath in source form (there&amp;#8217;s an option to have precompiled type checking extensions but this is beyond the scope of this blog post):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;SecureExtension1.groovy&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;onMethodSelection { expr, methodNode -&amp;gt;					&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;
   if (methodNode.declaringClass.name==&apos;java.lang.System&apos;) {		&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
      addStaticTypeError(&quot;Method call is not allowed!&quot;, expr)		&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
   }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;when the type checker selects the target method of a call&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;then if the selected method belongs to the &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; class&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;make the type checker throw an error&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s really all needed. Now execute the code again, and you will see that there&amp;#8217;s a compile time error!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;/home/cchampeau/tmp/securetest.groovy: 6: [Static type checking] - Method call is not allowed!
 @ line 6, column 3.
     c.exit(-1)
     ^

1 error&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this time, thanks to the type checker, &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; is really recognized as an instance of class &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; and we can really disallow the call. This is a very simple example, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t really go as
far as what we can do with the secure AST customizer in terms of configuration. The extension that we wrote has &lt;strong&gt;hardcoded&lt;/strong&gt; checks, but it would probably be nicer if we could configure it. So let&amp;#8217;s
start working with a bit more complex example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that your application computes a score for a document and that you allow the users to customize the score. Then your DSL:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will expose (at least) a variable named &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will allow the user to perform mathematical operations (including calling methods like &lt;em&gt;cos&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;abs&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8230;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;should disallow all other method calls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of user script would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;abs(cos(1+score))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a DSL is easy to setup. It&amp;#8217;s a variant of the one we defined earlier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Sandbox.java&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;CompilerConfiguration conf = new CompilerConfiguration();
ImportCustomizer customizer = new ImportCustomizer();
customizer.addStaticStars(&quot;java.lang.Math&quot;);                        &lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;
conf.addCompilationCustomizers(customizer);
Binding binding = new Binding();
binding.setVariable(&quot;score&quot;, 2.0d);                                 &lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
GroovyShell shell = new GroovyShell(binding,conf);
Double userScore = (Double) shell.evaluate(&quot;abs(cos(1+score))&quot;);    &lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
System.out.println(&quot;userScore = &quot; + userScore);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;add an import customizer that will add &lt;code&gt;import static java.lang.Math.*&lt;/code&gt; to all scripts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;make the &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt; variable available to the script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;execute the script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;admonitionblock tip&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;icon&quot;&gt;
&lt;i class=&quot;icon-tip&quot; title=&quot;Tip&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
There are options to cache the scripts, instead of parsing and compiling them each time. Please check the documentation for more details.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, our script works, but nothing prevents a hacker from executing malicious code. Since we want to use type checking, I would recommand to use the &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic&lt;/code&gt; transformation
transparently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it will activate type checking on the script, and we will be able to perform additional checks thanks to the type checking extension&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it will improve the performance of the script&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic&lt;/code&gt; transparently is easy. We just have to update the compiler configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ASTTransformationCustomizer astcz = new ASTTransformationCustomizer(CompileStatic.class);
conf.addCompilationCustomizers(astcz);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you try to execute the script again, you will face a compile time error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;Script1.groovy: 1: [Static type checking] - The variable [score] is undeclared.
 @ line 1, column 11.
   abs(cos(1+score))
             ^

Script1.groovy: 1: [Static type checking] - Cannot find matching method int#plus(java.lang.Object). Please check if the declared type is right and if the method exists.
 @ line 1, column 9.
   abs(cos(1+score))
           ^

2 errors&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? If you read the script from a &quot;compiler&quot; point of view, it doesn&amp;#8217;t know anything about the &quot;score&quot; variable. &lt;strong&gt;You&lt;/strong&gt;, as a developer, know that it&amp;#8217;s a variable
of type &lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;, but the compiler cannot infer it. This is precisely what type checking extensions are designed for: you can provide additional information to the compiler,
so that compilation passes. In this case, we will want to indicate that the &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt; variable is of type &lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we will slightly change the way we transparently add the &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic&lt;/code&gt; annotation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ASTTransformationCustomizer astcz = new ASTTransformationCustomizer(
        singletonMap(&quot;extensions&quot;, singletonList(&quot;SecureExtension2.groovy&quot;)),
        CompileStatic.class);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will &quot;emulate&quot; code annotated with &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic(extensions=[&apos;SecureExtension2.groovy&apos;])&lt;/code&gt;. Of course now we need to write the extension which will recognize the &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt; variable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;SecureExtension2.groovy&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;unresolvedVariable { var -&amp;gt;			&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;
   if (var.name==&apos;score&apos;) {			&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
      return makeDynamic(var, double_TYPE)	&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
   }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in case the type checker cannot resolve a variable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;if the variable name is &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;then instruct the compiler to resolve the variable dynamically, and that the type of the variable is &lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a complete description of the type checking extension DSL in &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/#&quot;&gt;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;type_checking_extensions[this section of the documentation],
but you have here an example of _mixed mode compilation&lt;/em&gt; : the compiler is not able to resolve the &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt; variable. You, as the designer of the DSL, &lt;strong&gt;know&lt;/strong&gt; that the variable is in fact
found in the binding, and is of the &lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;, so the &lt;code&gt;makeDynamic&lt;/code&gt; call is here to tell the compiler: &quot;ok, don&amp;#8217;t worry, I know what I am doing, this variable can be resolved dynamically
and it will be of type &lt;code&gt;double&lt;/code&gt;&quot;. That&amp;#8217;s it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_first_completed_secure_extension&quot;&gt;First completed &quot;secure&quot; extension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;#8217;s time to put this altogether. We wrote a type checking extension which is capable of preventing calls on &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt; on one side, and we wrote another which is able to resolve the &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt;
variable on another. So if we combine both, we have a first, complete, securing type checking extension:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;SecureExtension3.groovy&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// disallow calls on System
onMethodSelection { expr, methodNode -&amp;gt;
    if (methodNode.declaringClass.name==&apos;java.lang.System&apos;) {
        addStaticTypeError(&quot;Method call is not allowed!&quot;, expr)
    }
}

// resolve the score variable
unresolvedVariable { var -&amp;gt;
    if (var.name==&apos;score&apos;) {
        return makeDynamic(var, double_TYPE)
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t forget to update the configuration in your Java class to use the new type checking extension:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ASTTransformationCustomizer astcz = new ASTTransformationCustomizer(
        singletonMap(&quot;extensions&quot;, singletonList(&quot;SecureExtension3.groovy&quot;)),
	CompileStatic.class);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Execute the code again and it still works. Now, try to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;abs(cos(1+score))
System.exit(-1)&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the script compilation will fail with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;Script1.groovy: 1: [Static type checking] - Method call is not allowed!
 @ line 1, column 19.
   abs(cos(1+score));System.exit(-1)
                     ^

1 error&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, you just wrote your first type checking extension that prevents the execution of malicious code!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_improving_configuration_of_the_extension&quot;&gt;Improving configuration of the extension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far so good, we are able to prevent calls on &lt;code&gt;System&lt;/code&gt;, but it is likely that we are going to discover new vulnerabilities, and that we will want to
prevent execution of such code. So instead of hardcoding everything in the extension, we will try to make our extension generic and configurable. This is
probably the trickiest thing to do, because there&amp;#8217;s no direct way to provide context to a type checking extension. Our idea therefore relies on the (ugly)
thread locals to pass configuration data to the type checker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing we&amp;#8217;re going to do is to make the variable list configurable. Here is the code on the Java side of things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Sandbox.java&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class Sandbox {
    public static final String VAR_TYPES = &quot;sandboxing.variable.types&quot;;

    public static final ThreadLocal&amp;lt;Map&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt;&amp;gt; COMPILE_OPTIONS = new ThreadLocal&amp;lt;&amp;gt;();		&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        CompilerConfiguration conf = new CompilerConfiguration();
        ImportCustomizer customizer = new ImportCustomizer();
        customizer.addStaticStars(&quot;java.lang.Math&quot;);
        ASTTransformationCustomizer astcz = new ASTTransformationCustomizer(
                singletonMap(&quot;extensions&quot;, singletonList(&quot;SecureExtension4.groovy&quot;)),			&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
                CompileStatic.class);
        conf.addCompilationCustomizers(astcz);
        conf.addCompilationCustomizers(customizer);

        Binding binding = new Binding();
        binding.setVariable(&quot;score&quot;, 2.0d);
        try {
            Map&amp;lt;String,ClassNode&amp;gt; variableTypes = new HashMap&amp;lt;String, ClassNode&amp;gt;();			&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
            variableTypes.put(&quot;score&quot;, ClassHelper.double_TYPE);					&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(4)&lt;/b&gt;
            Map&amp;lt;String,Object&amp;gt; options = new HashMap&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt;();					&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(5)&lt;/b&gt;
            options.put(VAR_TYPES, variableTypes);							&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(6)&lt;/b&gt;
            COMPILE_OPTIONS.set(options);								&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(7)&lt;/b&gt;
            GroovyShell shell = new GroovyShell(binding, conf);
            Double userScore = (Double) shell.evaluate(&quot;abs(cos(1+score));System.exit(-1)&quot;);
            System.out.println(&quot;userScore = &quot; + userScore);
        } finally {
            COMPILE_OPTIONS.remove();									&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(8)&lt;/b&gt;
        }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;create a &lt;code&gt;ThreadLocal&lt;/code&gt; that will hold the contextual configuration of the type checking extension&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;update the extension to &lt;code&gt;SecureExtension4.groovy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;variableTypes&lt;/code&gt; is a map variable name &amp;#8594; variable type&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;so this is where we&amp;#8217;re going to add the &lt;code&gt;score&lt;/code&gt; variable declaration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;options&lt;/code&gt; is the map that will store our type checking configuration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;6&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;we set the &quot;variable types&quot; value of this configuration map to the map of variable types&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;7&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;and assign it to the thread local&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;8&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;eventually, to avoid memory leaks, it is important to remove the configuration from the thread local&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, here is how the type checking extension can use this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import static Sandbox.*

def typesOfVariables = COMPILE_OPTIONS.get()[VAR_TYPES]				&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;

unresolvedVariable { var -&amp;gt;
    if (typesOfVariables[var.name]) {						&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
        return makeDynamic(var, typesOfVariables[var.name])			&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Retrieve the list of variable types from the thread local&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;if an unresolved variable is found in the map of known variables&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;then declare to the type checker that the variable is of the type found in the map&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, the type checking extension, because it is executed when the type checker verifies the script, can access the
configuration through the thread local. Then, instead of using hard coded names in &lt;code&gt;unresolvedVariable&lt;/code&gt;, we can just check
that the variable that the type checker doesn&amp;#8217;t know about is actually declared in the configuration. If it is, then we
can tell it which type it is. Easy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have to find a way to explicitly declare the list of allowed method calls. It is a bit trickier to find a proper
configuration for that, but here is what we came up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_configuring_a_white_list_of_methods&quot;&gt;Configuring a white list of methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the whitelist is simple. A method call will be allowed if the method descriptor can be found in the whitelist. This whitelist consists of regular expressions, and
the method descriptor consists of the fully-qualified class name of the method, it&amp;#8217;s name and parameters. For example, for &lt;code&gt;System.exit&lt;/code&gt;, the descriptor would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;java.lang.System#exit(int)&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;#8217;s see how to update the Java integration part to add this configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class Sandbox {
    public static final String WHITELIST_PATTERNS = &quot;sandboxing.whitelist.patterns&quot;;

    // ...

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        // ...
        try {
            Map&amp;lt;String,ClassNode&amp;gt; variableTypes = new HashMap&amp;lt;String, ClassNode&amp;gt;();
            variableTypes.put(&quot;score&quot;, ClassHelper.double_TYPE);
            Map&amp;lt;String,Object&amp;gt; options = new HashMap&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt;();
            List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; patterns = new ArrayList&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;();					&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;
            patterns.add(&quot;java\\.lang\\.Math#&quot;);						&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;
            options.put(VAR_TYPES, variableTypes);
            options.put(WHITELIST_PATTERNS, patterns);						&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
            COMPILE_OPTIONS.set(options);
            GroovyShell shell = new GroovyShell(binding, conf);
            Double userScore = (Double) shell.evaluate(&quot;abs(cos(1+score));System.exit(-1)&quot;);
            System.out.println(&quot;userScore = &quot; + userScore);
        } finally {
            COMPILE_OPTIONS.remove();
        }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;declare a list of patterns&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;add all methods of &lt;code&gt;java.lang.Math&lt;/code&gt; as allowed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;put the whitelist to the type checking options map&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on the type checking extension side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import groovy.transform.CompileStatic
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.ClassNode
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.MethodNode
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.Parameter
import org.codehaus.groovy.transform.stc.ExtensionMethodNode

import static Sandbox.*

@CompileStatic
private static String prettyPrint(ClassNode node) {
    node.isArray()?&quot;${prettyPrint(node.componentType)}[]&quot;:node.toString(false)
}

@CompileStatic
private static String toMethodDescriptor(MethodNode node) {								&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(1)&lt;/b&gt;
    if (node instanceof ExtensionMethodNode) {
        return toMethodDescriptor(node.extensionMethodNode)
    }
    def sb = new StringBuilder()
    sb.append(node.declaringClass.toString(false))
    sb.append(&quot;#&quot;)
    sb.append(node.name)
    sb.append(&apos;(&apos;)
    sb.append(node.parameters.collect { Parameter it -&amp;gt;
        prettyPrint(it.originType)
    }.join(&apos;,&apos;))
    sb.append(&apos;)&apos;)
    sb
}
def typesOfVariables = COMPILE_OPTIONS.get()[VAR_TYPES]
def whiteList = COMPILE_OPTIONS.get()[WHITELIST_PATTERNS]								&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(2)&lt;/b&gt;

onMethodSelection { expr, MethodNode methodNode -&amp;gt;
    def descr = toMethodDescriptor(methodNode)										&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(3)&lt;/b&gt;
    if (!whiteList.any { descr =~ it }) {										&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(4)&lt;/b&gt;
        addStaticTypeError(&quot;You tried to call a method which is not allowed, what did you expect?: $descr&quot;, expr)	&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;(5)&lt;/b&gt;
    }
}

unresolvedVariable { var -&amp;gt;
    if (typesOfVariables[var.name]) {
        return makeDynamic(var, typesOfVariables[var.name])
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;colist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;this method will generate a method descriptor from a &lt;code&gt;MethodNode&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;retrieve the whitelist of methods from the thread local option map&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;convert a selected method into a descriptor string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;conum&quot; data-value=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;b&gt;4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;if the descriptor doesn&amp;#8217;t match any of the whitelist entries, throw an error&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you execute the code again, you will now have a very cool error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;Script1.groovy: 1: [Static type checking] - You tried to call a method which is not allowed, what did you expect?: java.lang.System#exit(int)
 @ line 1, column 19.
   abs(cos(1+score));System.exit(-1)
                     ^

1 error&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There we are! We now have a type checking extension which handles both the types of the variables that you export in the binding &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;
a whitelist of allowed methods. This is still not perfect, but we&amp;#8217;re very close to the final solution! It&amp;#8217;s not perfect because we only
took care of method calls here, but you have to deal with more than that. For example, properties (like &lt;code&gt;foo.text&lt;/code&gt; which is implicitly
converted into &lt;code&gt;foo.getText()&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_putting_it_altogether&quot;&gt;Putting it altogether&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dealing with properties is a bit more complicated because the type checker doesn&amp;#8217;t have a handler for &quot;property selection&quot; like it does
for methods. We can work around that, and if you are interested in seeing the resulting code, check it out below. It&amp;#8217;s
a type checking extension which is not written exactly as you have seen in this blog post, because it is meant to be precompiled
for improved performance. But the idea is exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;SandboxingTypeCheckingExtension.groovy&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import groovy.transform.CompileStatic
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.ClassCodeVisitorSupport
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.ClassHelper
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.ClassNode
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.MethodNode
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.Parameter
import org.codehaus.groovy.ast.expr.PropertyExpression
import org.codehaus.groovy.control.SourceUnit
import org.codehaus.groovy.transform.sc.StaticCompilationMetadataKeys
import org.codehaus.groovy.transform.stc.ExtensionMethodNode
import org.codehaus.groovy.transform.stc.GroovyTypeCheckingExtensionSupport
import org.codehaus.groovy.transform.stc.StaticTypeCheckingSupport

import static Sandbox.*

class SandboxingTypeCheckingExtension extends GroovyTypeCheckingExtensionSupport.TypeCheckingDSL {

    @CompileStatic
    private static String prettyPrint(ClassNode node) {
        node.isArray()?&quot;${prettyPrint(node.componentType)}[]&quot;:node.toString(false)
    }

    @CompileStatic
    private static String toMethodDescriptor(MethodNode node) {
        if (node instanceof ExtensionMethodNode) {
            return toMethodDescriptor(node.extensionMethodNode)
        }
        def sb = new StringBuilder()
        sb.append(node.declaringClass.toString(false))
        sb.append(&quot;#&quot;)
        sb.append(node.name)
        sb.append(&apos;(&apos;)
        sb.append(node.parameters.collect { Parameter it -&amp;gt;
            prettyPrint(it.originType)
        }.join(&apos;,&apos;))
        sb.append(&apos;)&apos;)
        sb
    }

    @Override
    Object run() {

        // Fetch white list of regular expressions of authorized method calls
        def whiteList = COMPILE_OPTIONS.get()[WHITELIST_PATTERNS]
        def typesOfVariables = COMPILE_OPTIONS.get()[VAR_TYPES]

        onMethodSelection { expr, MethodNode methodNode -&amp;gt;
            def descr = toMethodDescriptor(methodNode)
            if (!whiteList.any { descr =~ it }) {
                addStaticTypeError(&quot;You tried to call a method which is not allowed, what did you expect?: $descr&quot;, expr)
            }
        }

        unresolvedVariable { var -&amp;gt;
            if (isDynamic(var) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; typesOfVariables[var.name]) {
                storeType(var, typesOfVariables[var.name])
                handled = true
            }
        }

        // handling properties (like foo.text) is harder because the type checking extension
        // does not provide a specific hook for this. Harder, but not impossible!

        afterVisitMethod { methodNode -&amp;gt;
            def visitor = new PropertyExpressionChecker(context.source, whiteList)
            visitor.visitMethod(methodNode)
        }
    }

    private class PropertyExpressionChecker extends ClassCodeVisitorSupport {
        private final SourceUnit unit
        private final List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; whiteList

        PropertyExpressionChecker(final SourceUnit unit, final List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; whiteList) {
            this.unit = unit
            this.whiteList = whiteList
        }

        @Override
        protected SourceUnit getSourceUnit() {
            unit
        }

        @Override
        void visitPropertyExpression(final PropertyExpression expression) {
            super.visitPropertyExpression(expression)

            ClassNode owner = expression.objectExpression.getNodeMetaData(StaticCompilationMetadataKeys.PROPERTY_OWNER)
            if (owner) {
                if (expression.spreadSafe &amp;amp;&amp;amp; StaticTypeCheckingSupport.implementsInterfaceOrIsSubclassOf(owner, classNodeFor(Collection))) {
                    owner = typeCheckingVisitor.inferComponentType(owner, ClassHelper.int_TYPE)
                }
                def descr = &quot;${prettyPrint(owner)}#${expression.propertyAsString}&quot;
                if (!whiteList.any { descr =~ it }) {
                    addStaticTypeError(&quot;Property is not allowed: $descr&quot;, expression)
                }
            }
        }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a final version of the sandbox that includes assertions to make sure that we catch all cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Sandbox.java&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class Sandbox {
    public static final String WHITELIST_PATTERNS = &quot;sandboxing.whitelist.patterns&quot;;
    public static final String VAR_TYPES = &quot;sandboxing.variable.types&quot;;

    public static final ThreadLocal&amp;lt;Map&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt;&amp;gt; COMPILE_OPTIONS = new ThreadLocal&amp;lt;Map&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt;&amp;gt;();

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        CompilerConfiguration conf = new CompilerConfiguration();
        ImportCustomizer customizer = new ImportCustomizer();
        customizer.addStaticStars(&quot;java.lang.Math&quot;);
        ASTTransformationCustomizer astcz = new ASTTransformationCustomizer(
                singletonMap(&quot;extensions&quot;, singletonList(&quot;SandboxingTypeCheckingExtension.groovy&quot;)),
                CompileStatic.class);
        conf.addCompilationCustomizers(astcz);
        conf.addCompilationCustomizers(customizer);

        Binding binding = new Binding();
        binding.setVariable(&quot;score&quot;, 2.0d);
        try {
            Map&amp;lt;String, ClassNode&amp;gt; variableTypes = new HashMap&amp;lt;String, ClassNode&amp;gt;();
            variableTypes.put(&quot;score&quot;, ClassHelper.double_TYPE);
            Map&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt; options = new HashMap&amp;lt;String, Object&amp;gt;();
            List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; patterns = new ArrayList&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;();
            // allow method calls on Math
            patterns.add(&quot;java\\.lang\\.Math#&quot;);
            // allow constructors calls on File
            patterns.add(&quot;File#&amp;lt;init&amp;gt;&quot;);
            // because we let the user call each/times/...
            patterns.add(&quot;org\\.codehaus\\.groovy\\.runtime\\.DefaultGroovyMethods&quot;);
            options.put(VAR_TYPES, variableTypes);
            options.put(WHITELIST_PATTERNS, patterns);
            COMPILE_OPTIONS.set(options);
            GroovyShell shell = new GroovyShell(binding, conf);
            Object result;
            try {
                result = shell.evaluate(&quot;Eval.me(&apos;1&apos;)&quot;); // error
                assert false;
            } catch (MultipleCompilationErrorsException e) {
                System.out.println(&quot;Successful sandboxing: &quot;+e.getMessage());
            }
            try {
                result = shell.evaluate(&quot;System.exit(-1)&quot;); // error
                assert false;
            } catch (MultipleCompilationErrorsException e) {
                System.out.println(&quot;Successful sandboxing: &quot;+e.getMessage());
            }
            try {
                result = shell.evaluate(&quot;((Object)Eval).me(&apos;1&apos;)&quot;); // error
                assert false;
            } catch (MultipleCompilationErrorsException e) {
                System.out.println(&quot;Successful sandboxing: &quot;+e.getMessage());
            }

            try {
                result = shell.evaluate(&quot;new File(&apos;/etc/passwd&apos;).getText()&quot;); // getText is not allowed
                assert false;
            } catch (MultipleCompilationErrorsException e) {
                System.out.println(&quot;Successful sandboxing: &quot;+e.getMessage());
            }

            try {
                result = shell.evaluate(&quot;new File(&apos;/etc/passwd&apos;).text&quot;);  // getText is not allowed
                assert false;
            } catch (MultipleCompilationErrorsException e) {
                System.out.println(&quot;Successful sandboxing: &quot;+e.getMessage());
            }

            Double userScore = (Double) shell.evaluate(&quot;abs(cos(1+score))&quot;);
            System.out.println(&quot;userScore = &quot; + userScore);
        } finally {
            COMPILE_OPTIONS.remove();
        }
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post has explored the interest of using Groovy as a platform for scripting on the JVM. It introduced various mechanisms for integration, and showed that this
comes at the price of security. However, we illustrated some concepts like compilation customizers that make it easier to sandbox the environment of execution of
scripts. The current list of customizers available in the Groovy distribution, and the currently available sandboxing projects in the wild, are not sufficient
to guarantee security of execution of scripts in the general case (dependending, of course, on your users and where the scripts come from).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then illustrated how you could, if you are ready to pay the price of loosing some of the dynamic features of the language, properly workaround those limitations
through type checking extensions. Those type checking extensions are so powerful that you can even introduce your own error messages during the compilation of
scripts. Eventually, by doing this and caching your scripts, you will also benefit from dramatic performance improvements in script execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the sandboxing mechanism that we illustrated is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a replacement for the &lt;code&gt;SecureASTCustomizer&lt;/code&gt;. We recommand that you actually use &lt;strong&gt;both&lt;/strong&gt;, because they
work on different levels: the secure AST customizer will work on the grammar level, allowing you to restrict some language constructs (for example preventing the
creation of closures or classes inside the script), while the type checking extension will work after type inference (allowing you to reason on inferred types
rather than declared types).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the solution that I described here is incomplete. It is not available in Groovy core. As I will have less time to work on Groovy, I would be very
glad if someone or some people improve this solution and make a pull request so that we can have something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who is Groovy?</title>
      <link>http://melix.github.io/blog/2015/02/who-is-groovy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 4 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/02/who-is-groovy.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;div id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the changes that the Groovy project is seeing since the beginning of the year, I thought it was a good time to
make a summary about its history. In particular, with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.pivotal.io/pivotal/news-2/groovy-2-4-and-grails-3-0-to-be-last-major-releases-under-pivotal-sponsorship&quot;&gt;end of sponsorship from Pivotal&lt;/a&gt;, as well as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://restlet.com/blog/2015/03/02/head-of-groovy-project-joins-restlet-to-lead-api-development-tools/&quot;&gt;Guillaume Laforge annoucing he is joining Restlet&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of people state that Groovy is done. It will be the occasion to talk about
the history of the project, both in terms of community and sponsorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, Groovy is, and will remain, alive. Groovy is a community project and we are pleased to announce that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://glaforge.appspot.com/article/groovy-projects-intends-to-join-the-apache-software-foundation&quot;&gt;Groovy
has started the process to join the Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. The community deserved it, and even if it will mean some adaptations on
our side, we think that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://apache.org&quot;&gt;ASF&lt;/a&gt; will be a great fit for the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To build the statistics you will read in this post, I have used a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/melix/blog/blob/master/src/jbake/content/2015/02/commit-stats.groovy&quot;&gt;Groovy script&lt;/a&gt; (of course!) that
takes as reference the number of commits. This is far from being a perfect number, because some commits are just
for fixing typos, while others are full new features and it also totally misses the fact that patches, before Git, didn&amp;#8217;t carry the author
information or the problem that we maintain multiple branches
of Groovy, requiring a lot of work, but it gives an idea&amp;#8230; And because people think that end of sponsorship
may be equivalent to death, I separated commits in two categories: sponsored and community. Sponsored commits are commits
which are likely to have been made by someone directly paid to contribute on Groovy. We will see how this proportion evolved
over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think Groovy is dead, please read the following carefully. Let&amp;#8217;s start our journey back in time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2003_a_dynamic_language_for_the_jvm&quot;&gt;2003: A dynamic language for the JVM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 476 commits &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 476 commits (100%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;James Strachan : 374 commits (78%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boc McWhirter : 76 commits (15%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Pullara : 23 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kasper Nielsen : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aslak Hellesoy : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2003 is the inception year of Groovy. &lt;strong&gt;James Strachan&lt;/strong&gt;, in August 2003, wanted to create a dynamic language for the JVM, inspired by Ruby,
but closer to Java. Groovy was born, and the idea never changed over time: Groovy is the perfect companion for Java, a language which can
be very close to Java in terms of syntax but also removes a lot of its boilerplate. Bob McWhirter is a famous name in the JVM world, he is
now Director of Polyglot at Red Hat, so you can see that when he started contributing to the language back then, there was already a story
for him! Sam Pullara is another very smart guy in the JVM world and he worked for top companies like BEA, Yahoo! or Twitter to name a few.
He is a technical reviewer for the JavaOne conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2004_guillaume_laforge_joins_the_project&quot;&gt;2004: Guillaume Laforge joins the project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 871 commits &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 871 commits (100%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;James Strachan : 495 commits (56%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge : 101 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wilson : 70 commits (8%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Pullara : 66 commits (7%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Rayner : 33 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Poirier : 28 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bing Ran : 21 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Goetze : 12 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Stump : 10 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zohar Melamed : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou : 7 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damage Control : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boc McWhirter : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christiaan ten Klooster : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yuri Schimke : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groovy is hosted at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codehaus.org/&quot;&gt;Codehaus&lt;/a&gt; (which just has annouced its retirement) and 2004 sees the appearance of famous names of the community. In particular,
you can already see &lt;strong&gt;Guillaume Laforge&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Jochen Theodorou&lt;/strong&gt;. Both of them still directly work on the project as today. John Wilson started contributing
the famous XML support of Groovy, and you can also note names like Russel Winder of Gant and &lt;a href=&quot;http://gpars.codehaus.org/&quot;&gt;GPars&lt;/a&gt; fame. Jeremy Rayer&amp;#8217;s work is famous in the Groovy
community since he wrote the first versions of the Groovy grammar using Antlr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2005_jochen_theodorou_joins_the_project&quot;&gt;2005: Jochen Theodorou joins the project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 934 commits &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 934 commits (100%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Jochen Theodorou : 244 commits (26%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Strachan : 162 commits (17%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pilho Kim : 104 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wilson : 79 commits (8%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge : 75 commits (8%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dierk Koenig : 70 commits (7%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Rayner : 62 commits (6%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian Stein : 48 commits (5%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Green : 20 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 20 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin C. Martin : 14 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Pullara : 10 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Rose : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hein Meling : 7 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott Stirling : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franck Rasolo : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would tend to think that 2005 is the year when Jochen Theodorou took the technical lead of Groovy. In 2005, he becomes the most prolific contributor,
even beyond the creator of the language himself. Dierk Koenig makes an appearance here: he is known for his work on &lt;a href=&quot;http://gpars.codehaus.org/&quot;&gt;GPars&lt;/a&gt;, but also for the reference book for Groovy: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.manning.com/koenig2/&quot;&gt;Groovy in Action&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2006_rise_of_paul_king&quot;&gt;2006: Rise of Paul King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 480 commits &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 480 commits (100%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Jochen Theodorou : 221 commits (46%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wilson : 56 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul King : 54 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge : 47 commits (9%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dierk Koenig : 37 commits (7%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Rayner : 23 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 14 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Alleon : 12 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joachim Baumann : 6 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin C. Martin : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme Rocher : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Guillemot : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian Stein : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Goetze : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2006 is a very calm year for Groovy in terms of code production. James, the creator of the language, already disappeared from the contributors, and will not contribute anymore. &lt;strong&gt;Guillaume Laforge&lt;/strong&gt;, in agreement with the other contributors, &lt;strong&gt;takes the project lead&lt;/strong&gt; (he is still the lead today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With half as many commits as in 2007, in retrospect, I would say that this was a critical year: either the project would die, or it would have become what it is today. And my personal feeling is that the person who saved Groovy just appeared in the contributors list: Paul King. &lt;strong&gt;Paul is undoubtfully the most active contributor to Groovy&lt;/strong&gt;. He wrote a lot of the Groovy Development Kit, that is to say the APIs without which a language would be nothing. Having a nice language is one thing, having proper APIs and libraries that unleash its full potential is another. Paul King did it. Look at his ranking here: 3rd place. You will never see him ranked lower than that. And guess what? Paul is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; paid to do this. He &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.asert.com.au/&quot;&gt;runs his own business&lt;/a&gt; and if you want to work with a Groovy expert, he&amp;#8217;s probably the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joachim Baumann is a name some people would recognize: he is still working with Groovy and one of the most regular contributors, with the Windows installer. Joachim takes time, for each Groovy release, to produce a Windows installer, which today we are still not capable of handling automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2007_groovy_1_0&quot;&gt;2007: Groovy 1.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Paul King : 447 commits (30%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Dillon : 265 commits (18%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 242 commits (16%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danno Ferrin : 101 commits (6%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Tkachman (Sponsored) : 87 commits (5%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme Rocher (Sponsored) : 61 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 46 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Guillemot : 36 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 34 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 33 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Rayner : 26 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandru Popescu : 24 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wilson : 22 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joachim Baumann : 21 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Brown : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dierk Koenig : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin C. Martin : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Alleon : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2007 is an important year in the history of Groovy. On January, 2d, Groovy 1.0 is out. &lt;strong&gt;Paul King ranks #1 for the first time, and will
remain on top for a long time&lt;/strong&gt;. This year also sees the creation of G2One, the first company build specifically for Groovy and Grails, by Guillaume
Laforge, Graeme Rocher and Alex Tkachman. Both Graeme and Alex make their first appearance in the contributors graph, and both of them made
significant contributions to the Groovy ecosystem: Graeme is famous for co-creating the Grails framework, and is still the lead of the project,
while Alex is the one who contributed major performance improvements to the Groovy runtime (call site caching) and first experimented with
a static compiler for Groovy (Groovy++).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danno Ferrin contributed what is still one of my personal favorite features of Groovy, AST transformations, and probably one of the reasons
I got paid to work on Groovy so thank you Danno! Andrés Almiray,
listed here for the first time, is famous for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://griffon.codehaus.org/&quot;&gt;Griffon&lt;/a&gt; framework, a Grails-like framework for desktop applications which is still
actively developed. He spent a lot of time improving the Swing support in Groovy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from 2007, you will see that the &lt;em&gt;sponsored&lt;/em&gt; ratio of commits is changing. People who were employed by G2One fall into that category. As you
can see, 2007 is more than important for Groovy, it is its second birth. And to conclude that, Groovy won the first prize at JAX 2007 innovation award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2008_the_g2one_era&quot;&gt;2008: The G2One era&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 1069 commits &lt;strong&gt;Sponsored&lt;/strong&gt;: 287 commits (26%) &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 782 commits (73%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Paul King : 445 commits (41%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danno Ferrin : 176 commits (16%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 126 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Tkachman (Sponsored) : 125 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 33 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim White : 32 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 31 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Kempf : 22 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roshan Dawrani : 19 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Rayner : 14 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin C. Martin : 12 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Dillon : 9 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thom Nichols : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme Rocher (Sponsored) : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Brown : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wilson : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Williams : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Guillemot : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vladimir Vivien : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2008, &lt;strong&gt;Paul King still ranks #1&lt;/strong&gt; and you can see that the people who were sponsored by G2One were actually not the main contributors. Actually, most
of them did consulting to pay salaries, which doesn&amp;#8217;t leave much time to contribute to the language. Hopefully, a great project such as Groovy can rely
on its community! Guillaume, Graeme and Alex were looking for an opportunity to spend more time on actual development, and it happened in November 2008
when G2One got acquired by SpringSource.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the contributors you see in this list are still actively using Groovy or contributing: Jim White for example is famous for his contributions on the scripting sides of the language. Roshan Dawrani is one of the few guys capable of opening cryptic code and fixing bugs. Jeff Brown is a name you should know, since he is now a key member of the Grails team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2009_milestones_and_the_inappropriate_quote&quot;&gt;2009: milestones and the inappropriate quote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 835 commits &lt;strong&gt;Sponsored&lt;/strong&gt;: 183 commits (21%) &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 652 commits (78%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Paul King : 342 commits (40%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roshan Dawrani : 128 commits (15%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 101 commits (12%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Tkachman (Sponsored) : 41 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 40 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Dillon : 31 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim White : 31 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danno Ferrin : 24 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Niederwieser : 23 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamlet D&amp;#8217;Arcy : 18 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 14 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin C. Martin : 13 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thom Nichols : 13 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 12 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vladimir Vivien : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graeme Rocher (Sponsored) : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2009 is another important year concluding with the release of Groovy 1.7, the first version of Groovy supporting inner classes
or the famous power asserts from Peter Niederwieser. If you know Groovy, you must know Peter, the father of the famous Spock testing
framework which &lt;a href=&quot;http://groovy.329449.n5.nabble.com/Ann-Spock-1-0-has-been-released-td5722915.html&quot;&gt;just reached 1.0&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hamlet D&amp;#8217;Arcy contributed a lot in terms of code quality&lt;/strong&gt;, but also became the first specialist of AST transformations. 2009 is also the year I started to use Groovy, as a user. I never stopped and actually I started contributing back
then. At that time, Groovy was still using Subversion (we&amp;#8217;re now using Git like all the cool kids), so it was the good old patch way,
loosing authorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year is also the year when James Strachan wrote a very famous quote about Groovy. This quote is probably the most innapropriately
used quote about Groovy of all time, because it was done by its creator, but remember that James left the project in 2005!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;quoteblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I can honestly say if someone had shown me the Programming in Scala book by Martin Odersky, Lex Spoon &amp;amp; Bill Venners back in 2003 I&amp;#8217;d probably have never created Groovy.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;on his blog&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;#8212; James Strachan
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all James says nothing about the language itself here. He had already left the project and says that &lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt; he had known about Scala before, he &lt;strong&gt;wouldn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/strong&gt; have created Groovy. I am today very happy that he didn&amp;#8217;t know about it, or we would have missed an incredibly powerful language. Groovy today
is &lt;strong&gt;nothing close&lt;/strong&gt; to what it was when James left the project, thanks to the lead of Guillaume Laforge and incredibly talented people like Paul King, Jochen Theodorou and all the contributors listed on this page. Groovy and Scala both have their communities, but also different use cases. I wouldn&amp;#8217;t sell one for the other&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end of 2009, another important milestone occurred for project, with VMware acquiring SpringSource.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2010_dsls_all_the_way&quot;&gt;2010: DSLs all the way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 894 commits &lt;strong&gt;Sponsored&lt;/strong&gt;: 189 commits (21%) &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 705 commits (78%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Paul King : 443 commits (49%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roshan Dawrani : 134 commits (14%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 96 commits (10%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 93 commits (10%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamlet D&amp;#8217;Arcy : 71 commits (7%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Tkachman : 28 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Niederwieser : 19 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 7 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Dillon : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russel Winder : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thom Nichols : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2010 is a pretty stable year for Groovy. Groovy reaches 1.8 in 2010 with important features for its incredible DSL design capabilities. With command chain expressions, native JSON support and performance improvements, Groovy put the bar very high in terms of integration in the Java ecosystem. Today, &lt;strong&gt;no other JVM language is as simple as Groovy to integrate with Java&lt;/strong&gt;. With cross-compilation and by the use of the very same class model, Groovy is at that date the best language for scripting on the JVM. It is so good that a lot of people start to see it as a better Java and want to use it as a first class language. However, being dynamic, Groovy is still a problem for a category of users&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2011_time_to_move_to_github&quot;&gt;2011: Time to move to GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 841 commits &lt;strong&gt;Sponsored&lt;/strong&gt;: 514 commits (61%) &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 327 commits (38%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Cédric Champeau (Sponsored) : 252 commits (29%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul King : 212 commits (25%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 163 commits (19%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 98 commits (11%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen : 44 commits (5%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamlet D&amp;#8217;Arcy : 33 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roshan Dawrani : 26 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Eisenberg : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Tkachman : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bobby Warner : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colin Harrington : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dierk Koenig : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dirk Weber : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wagenleitner : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lari Hotari (Sponsored) : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Niederwieser : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011, I became a committer to the Groovy project. As I said, I had contributed several fixes or features for Groovy 1.8, but for the first time, I became a committer and I started to be able to push changes to the codebase without having to ask permission. So this is basically the first time you see my name on the contributors list, but you can see that I am ranking #1 and I have never lost that ranking since then. It surprised me too, but there is a very good reason for that. In october 2011, in addition to being a committer, I also became paid to work on Groovy. Full-time. &lt;strong&gt;I entered the club of lucky people being paid to work on open-source software&lt;/strong&gt;. It was sincerely a dream, and I will never be enough thankful to Guillaume Laforge for giving me this opportunity. He changed my life and I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I became a better developer thanks to him. VMware was my employer back then, and while I had never worked on a language before, Guillaume trusted my skills and proposed to me to work on something that would dramatically change the language : a static type checker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also worked on the infrastructure of the language, starting from the migration to GitHub. It was an important move to make: as you can see, there was a very limited set of committers to Groovy. With &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/groovy/groovy-core/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, we had the tool we needed to increase the size of our community and from the numbers that will follow, I think it&amp;#8217;s a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2012_groovy_2_and_static_compilation&quot;&gt;2012: Groovy 2 and static compilation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Cédric Champeau (Sponsored) : 515 commits (46%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul King : 249 commits (22%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 169 commits (15%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 74 commits (6%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PascalSchumacher : 12 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Niederwieser : 11 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;René Scheibe : 11 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andre Steingress : 9 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wagenleitner : 7 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Ledbrook : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adrian Nistor : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Yates : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baruch Sadogursky : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Eisenberg : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rich Freedman : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephane Maldini : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Taylor : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Brown : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke Daley : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tiago Fernandez : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrey Bloschetsov : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johnny Wey : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenneth Kousen : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathieu Bruyen : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Bakker : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paulo Poiati : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sean Flanigan : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suk-Hyun Cho : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vladimir Orany : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2012 is one of the most important years for the language. It was the year Groovy 2.0 was released. As you can see, I am still ranking #1 and Paul King, an unpaid contributor, is #2. This tells you the importance of community! Groovy 2 is a major change in the language, because it introduced both optional type checking and static compilation. For the first time, Groovy was able to provide at compile time the same level of feedback that Java would have. Some people wanted to kill me for having introduced that into the language. The truth is that it wasn&amp;#8217;t my decision, but in retrospect, I am very happy with what the language is now. Without this, some people would have abandonned Groovy in favor of other JVM languages like Scala, while now in Groovy you can have the same level of performance as Java, with type safety, powerful type inference, extension methods, functional style programming and without the boilerplate. And it&amp;#8217;s optional. I don&amp;#8217;t know any other language that allows this, especially when you take type checking extensions into account, a feature that allows Groovy to go far beyond what Java and other languages offer in terms of type safety or static compilation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2012 also sees the appearance of Pascal Schumacher, a silent but very active Groovy committer. Pascal does since 2012 an amazing job in helping us filtering JIRA issues, writing bugfixes, reviewing pull requests and lately writing documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2013_documentation_effort_and_explosion_of_contributions&quot;&gt;2013: Documentation effort and explosion of contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Cédric Champeau (Sponsored) : 244 commits (22%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul King : 188 commits (17%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PascalSchumacher : 180 commits (16%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 96 commits (8%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thibault Kruse : 84 commits (7%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 54 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrey Bloschetsov : 43 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andre Steingress : 36 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pascal Schumacher : 27 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Yates : 24 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;René Scheibe : 12 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;kruset : 12 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Hauner : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry Jacobson : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wagenleitner : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paolo Di Tommaso : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Scott Brown (Sponsored) : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Masato Nagai : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Eddelbüttel : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hbaykuslar : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;shalecraig : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Eisenberg : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jacopo Cappellato : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Niederwieser : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rafael Luque : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vladimir Orany : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;saschaklein : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;seanjreilly : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;upcrob : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adrian Nistor : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Thompson : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alessio Stalla : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DJBen : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Dahl : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ingo Hoffmann : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JBaruch : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jacob Aae Mikkelsen : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim White : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Engelman : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon Schneider : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karel Piwko : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenneth Endfinger : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kohsuke Kawaguchi : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke Kirby : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michal Mally : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miro Bezjak : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olivier Croquette : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob Upcraft : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergey Egorov : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stefan Armbruster : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yasuharu NAKANO : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While continuing to improve Groovy, 2013 was very important for the community. You can start to see the GitHub effect here, with &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; more contributors than before. It is impressive to see the difference before 2011 and after. The number of contributors is continously growing. In 2013, 63% of commits came from the community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2013, we also launched a new big project: the documentation and website overhaul. It is incredible to think that this effort is still uncomplete, but if you see that the old wiki has more than a thousand page or contents (often outdated), you can imagine what effort it takes to rewrite the documentation. Hopefully, we&amp;#8217;re close to filling the gap now, and with the demise of Codehaus, we officially launched our &lt;a href=&quot;http://groovy-lang.org&quot;&gt;new website&lt;/a&gt; where you can see the result of this job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also started working on Android support during 2013, for a first overview in GR8Conf 2014, and continued working on improving the infrastructure, with Bintray, TeamCity and Gradle. And Pivotal was born, out of EMC and VMware. Groovy and Grails, along with the Spring Framework, became part of this new company which is still paying me today to work on Groovy (and I, we, should be very thankful for this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2014_towards_android_support&quot;&gt;2014: Towards Android support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Cédric Champeau (Sponsored) : 446 commits (37%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul King : 261 commits (22%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 85 commits (7%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Laforge (Sponsored) : 61 commits (5%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thibault Kruse : 54 commits (4%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pascal Schumacher : 47 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim White : 26 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yu Kobayashi : 18 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andre Steingress : 16 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Hightower : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Northrop : 11 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenneth Endfinger : 9 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomek Janiszewski : 9 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matias Bjarland : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tobia Conforto : 8 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Schuenck : 7 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sargis Harutyunyan : 7 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrey Bloschetsov : 6 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig Andrews : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kent : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paolo Di Tommaso : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Ledbrook : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergey Egorov : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yasuharu Nakano : 5 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Hamilton : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lari Hotari (Sponsored) : 4 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bloshchetsov Andrey Evgenyevich : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johannes Link : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keegan Witt : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Yates : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anto_belgin : 3 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baruch Sadogursky : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Allen : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan Sykora : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wagenleitner : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke Kirby : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Stockhammer : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UEHARA Junji : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vihang D : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andres Almiray : 2 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy Hamilton : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bobby Warner : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carsten Lenz : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Earle : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Avenante : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Nahodil : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Tiselius : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dimitar Dimitrov : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant McConnaughey : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Sheets : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jess Sightler : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logan Gorence : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke Daley : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manuel Prinz : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Guillemot : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marcin Grzejszczak : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan Mische : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Swire : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sagar Sane : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Mallette : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tobias Schulte : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wil Selwood : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;davidmichaelkarr : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fintelia : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;kruset : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;paul-bjorkstrand : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2014 was a difficult year. We had a lot of work to do on the documentation side, new features to deliver (traits) and an important topic we definitely wanted to highlight: Android support. This took longer than expected, but in the end, the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.groovy-lang.org/releasenotes/groovy-2.4.html&quot;&gt;Groovy 2.4&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;#8217;re lucky to have half of the commits coming from the community here. Especially, lots of people helped us on the documentation. And it wasn&amp;#8217;t easy, because our documentation requires that every snippet of code that appears in the docs belongs to a unit test, to make sure that the documentation is always up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at the end of the year, we learnt from Pivotal that they would end sponsoring our jobs. It means that Guillaume Laforge, Jochen Theodorou and myself, for the Groovy team, plus Graeme Rocher, Jeff Brown and Lari Hotari, for the Grails team, were both loosing their jobs and full time to work on the project at the same time. This wasn&amp;#8217;t really a surprise and I am very happy I could work for so long on Groovy, full time, but as I said in a previous post I also wish I will still be able to do that, because you can see from the numbers and features that it matters. If you wonder, we are still discussing with several potential sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2015_your_story&quot;&gt;2015: Your story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: 178 commits &lt;strong&gt;Sponsored&lt;/strong&gt;: 81 commits (45%) &lt;strong&gt;Community&lt;/strong&gt;: 97 commits (54%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Cédric Champeau (Sponsored) : 69 commits (38%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pascal Schumacher : 59 commits (33%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jochen Theodorou (Sponsored) : 12 commits (6%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul King : 12 commits (6%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JBrownVisualSpection : 7 commits (3%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yu Kobayashi : 3 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christoph Frick : 2 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kamil Szymanski : 2 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Schuenck : 2 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sean Gilligan : 2 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergey Egorov : 2 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thibault Kruse : 2 commits (1%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy Wilkinson : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maksym Stavytskyi : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mario Garcia : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radovan Synek : 1 commits (0%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2015 will be another important year. It&amp;#8217;s going to be huge for the community. Guillaume Laforge announced that he was joining Restlet, so for the first time since 2007 he will not be fully employed to work on Groovy, but I don&amp;#8217;t expect this to have a big impact on the language development itself: as you can see from the numbers, about half of the commits already come from the community and Guillaume didn&amp;#8217;t contribute much code lately. He was instead the lead of the project, the one that took decisions, the one speaking about the project and talking to and leading the community. He was the voice. It was a hard job, a very important one for Groovy. Guillaume is still today the lead of the project, and he will continue to contribute to the language, but I know from him that he wanted to be able to do more code, and put Groovy in action into a new project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.pivotal.io/pivotal/news-2/groovy-2-4-and-grails-3-0-to-be-last-major-releases-under-pivotal-sponsorship&quot;&gt;end of sponsorship of Pivotal&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codehaus.org/&quot;&gt;demise of Codehaus&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://restlet.com/blog/2015/03/02/head-of-groovy-project-joins-restlet-to-lead-api-development-tools/&quot;&gt;Guillaume&amp;#8217;s decision&lt;/a&gt;, it became even more important to move Groovy to a foundation where it will be able to live with or without us. I have honestly no idea where I will work in a few weeks now. I sincerely hope I will still be able to contribute to the language full time, but let&amp;#8217;s be clear: today, it is very unlikely this is going to happen. It makes it very important for the project to be able to develop the community even more. We had more than 4.5 million downloads last year. This is huge. And with Android support, I see a lot of potential, even if we have tough competition with other languages and people being paid to develop them. The &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt; is going to help us with securing the future of the language and building a community&lt;/strong&gt;. I am proud of what you have done, collectively, and this is not over. Groovy is ready for a rebirth under the Apache umbrella!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than ever, the future of Groovy is you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude this post, here are the top 10 contributors, in terms of number of commits, of Groovy, for the past 12 years. Congratulations Paul and thanks to our 100+ contributors!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;olist arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Paul King :Paul King : 2653 commits (23%)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jochen Theodorou&lt;/strong&gt; : 1562 commits (13%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cédric Champeau&lt;/strong&gt; : 1526 commits (13%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;James Strachan&lt;/strong&gt; : 1031 commits (9%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guillaume Laforge&lt;/strong&gt; : 709 commits (6%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roshan Dawrani&lt;/strong&gt; : 307 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Dillon&lt;/strong&gt; : 306 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Danno Ferrin&lt;/strong&gt; : 301 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alex Tkachman&lt;/strong&gt; : 283 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Wilson&lt;/strong&gt; : 230 commits (2%)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking for a new job</title>
      <link>http://melix.github.io/blog/2015/01/for-hire.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2015/01/for-hire.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_will_you_be_the_new_groovy_sponsor&quot;&gt;Will you be the new Groovy sponsor?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There we are. January 19th was a bad day as Pivotal &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.pivotal.io/pivotal/news-2/groovy-2-4-and-grails-3-0-to-be-last-major-releases-under-pivotal-sponsorship&quot;&gt;announced that they wouldn&amp;#8217;t sponsor the development of the Groovy language&lt;/a&gt;, as well as its long time friend the Grails framework, starting from march 31st. As I was paid to work on Groovy, it has a direct consequence for me: starting from April 1st, I am &lt;strong&gt;for hire&lt;/strong&gt;. For you, it probably doesn&amp;#8217;t change much as Groovy and Grails existed before Pivotal without corporate funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was hard to keep this secret for weeks, but now that everything is public, it is easier for us. I have been lucky to work full time on the Groovy language for a bit more than 3 years now. Lucky because it was both a great open-source software and my passion. I have implemented major features of the language &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/groovy/groovy-core/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;since Groovy 1.8&lt;/a&gt;: static type checking, static compilation, Android support, numerous AST transformations, continous integration&amp;#8230; I have given talks to various conferences, including world class ones like JavaOne, Devoxx, GR8Conf or SpringOne2GX and it was a fantastic opportunity that wouldn&amp;#8217;t have been possible without the support from VMware then Pivotal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I feel that &lt;strong&gt;I still have a lot to do&lt;/strong&gt;. So many things are on the list, so much to improve, like for example adding language support for asynchronous programming, improved Java 8 support, a new meta-object protocol, not forgetting, of course, bugfixes&amp;#8230; I am 100% convinced that the language wouldn&amp;#8217;t have reached the level of maturity it has without support from a company like Pivotal. And even though Java is considered mature, it doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that the language shouldn&amp;#8217;t continue to evolve: it is rather the opposite. People are constantly asking for evolutions, because programming models evolve too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those reasons, my #1 choice would be to find a new company securing the development of Groovy and Grails, that is to say willing to pay me and my mates to continue working on them. The Groovy community is huge, there are lots of companies using Groovy in a variety of domains, I sincerely hope this is possible. With more than 4 million downloads in 2014, I can&amp;#8217;t imagine how many hours of development have been saved thanks to Groovy and Grails&amp;#8230; Should you be interested in sponsoring our projects, please write to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:sponsorship@groovy-lang.org&quot;&gt;sponsorship@groovy-lang.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_about_me&quot;&gt;About me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If unfortunately we can&amp;#8217;t find third parties willing to take over the development of the language and hire us, then I would obviously be available to help you in your projects. For those of you who are looking for someone with a good knowledge of the JVM internals, I am listening. My areas of interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&amp;amp;D&lt;/strong&gt;: innovation, technical challenges are what drive my motivation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;open-source&lt;/strong&gt; over closed-source: If you are an Open-Source company, by that I mean a company which contributes Open-Source, I think we are on the same line. I love to share what I do and I am convinced that open-source development is the best way to improve the global quality of a project. I have worked on closed-source software in the past, there are good reasons to do so but working on OSS software is really what I prefer. I also enjoy &lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/melix/&quot;&gt;speaking publicly&lt;/a&gt; about projects I work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JVM&lt;/strong&gt;: I have spent most of my career on that platform and believe me, it&amp;#8217;s not dead :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;back-end&lt;/strong&gt; over front-end: I love working on tooling, performance tuning, algorithmics&amp;#8230; everything that is hidden to the end user. On the other side I am not so good on the front-end part (HTML, CSS, &amp;#8230;) so it would probably not be a good idea to make me work on that topic :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;remote working&lt;/strong&gt;: I live in Saint Hilaire de Loulay, a small countryside town near Nantes, in France. I have now been working from home for more that 3 years, most of the Spring Framework team works that way, and it has been very successful so far. If you are not against the idea, I would love to continue that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case if you think a profile like mine is interesting for your company, you can contact me or ask for my résumé at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cedric.champeau@gmail.com&quot;&gt;cedric.champeau@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, rest assured that we are focused and we will soon release Groovy 2.4 to prove that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 things your static language can&amp;#8217;t do</title>
      <link>http://melix.github.io/blog/2014/12/10-things-static-cant-do.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2014/12/10-things-static-cant-do.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_but_maybe_mine_can&quot;&gt;But maybe mine can&amp;#8230;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who do not know me, and you are likely much more in that category than in the other, I&amp;#8217;ve been working on
the Groovy language full-time for more than 3 years now. I started as a user several years ago, in the context of DSLs,
and eventually became a contributor before getting employed to work on the language. I love static typing, but not at the
point of thinking that we should only reason about types. This is why I also love dynamic typing, and why I invested so
much in Groovy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groovy is primarily a dynamic language. It is probably the most widely used alternative language on the JVM, with use cases ranging
from DSLs (scripting Jenkins builds for example) to full blown applications on mobile devices (Android), going through
full stack web applications with Grails. Despite being primarily a dynamic language, I spent a lot of time writing a
&lt;strong&gt;static compiler for Groovy&lt;/strong&gt;, making it a pretty unique language in the JVM world, but not limited to the JVM world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groovy is a language which supports &lt;strong&gt;dynamic typing and compile-time type checking&lt;/strong&gt;. It makes it surprisingly powerful
and versatile language, capable of adapting to a great variety of contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tell people that I wrote the static compiler for Groovy, I often get a reaction which is &quot;so you admit that dynamic
languages are less powerful than static ones&quot;, and they see me as the one that made the language &lt;strong&gt;right&lt;/strong&gt;. Oh no, I did not.
In fact, I love the dynamic aspects of the language. It is always annoying that I, as a designer of a static compiler, have
to defend dynamic languages, but it&amp;#8217;s an interesting topic, especially those days where I read lots of articles doing
dynamic-bashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this post, I&amp;#8217;m going to illustrate 10 things that a static language (most likely) cannot do. It doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that there are only
10 things that a static language cannot do compared to a dynamic one, but it is here to illustrate the fact that this idea
that static languages are superior or more scalable just because they are &lt;em&gt;type safe&lt;/em&gt; is IMHO stupid. Compare languages between
them, but do not compare categories of languages. While static languages will be excellent in making type safety guarantees (errors
at compile time), dynamic languages are often far superior in cutting down verbosity. That&amp;#8217;s just an example which illustrates
that comparing on the sole aspect of type safety is not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will also illustrate how Groovy is special, because it is capable of handling things in a &lt;strong&gt;mixed&lt;/strong&gt; mode, making it
totally unique and incredibly powerful, bringing the best of the two worlds together. Last disclaimer, this post is mostly centered on
the JVM world, because this is the one I know the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;admonitionblock caution&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;icon&quot;&gt;
&lt;i class=&quot;icon-caution&quot; title=&quot;Caution&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
As expected I got lots of comments on various social media. Some are positive, some not, that&amp;#8217;s ok, but again, I
would like to remember that this is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; static languages bashing, nor dynamic languages promotion. Maybe some of you
will think &quot;hey, but my static language can do it!&quot; and yes, it is possible, because as the subtitle of this post says,
mine can too. But when it does, often, there&amp;#8217;s a drawback (like loosing type safety, decreased performance,&amp;#8230; ) or you fall on
dynamic behavior without even noticing it. When it is the case, I tried to be honest and tell about the possibilities. But I also
voluntarily hide some static features of Groovy that make it a very interesting solution (flow typing for example). Last but not
least, I am not saying that &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; dynamic features implement &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; those items. I am saying that by nature a dynamic language make
it possible. An possible doesn&amp;#8217;t mean required. So please read carefully before screaming!
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ready?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_10_object_oriented_programming_done_right&quot;&gt;10. Object-oriented programming done right&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very academic point of view. Users of static languages tend to think that their language is object-oriented. Because C++
has a compiler, because Java has a compiler, means that statically typed languages have to be compiled. Object oriented programming
does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; require languages to be compiled. OOP is about &lt;strong&gt;message passing&lt;/strong&gt;. Object-oriented programming does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; imply type safety.
It means that an object is something that receives messages. In the Java world, the message is a method with arguments, and the contract
is enforced at compile time, but it is an implementation detail which reduces OO programming to a small subset of its capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great Alan Kay himself &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.squeakfoundation.org/pipermail/squeak-dev/1998-October/017019.html&quot;&gt;explains it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groovy, as a dynamic language, supports commons OOP concepts (and also functional concepts) like class, interface, abstract classes or traits
but also has a meta-object protocol. For those of you who did Smalltalk programming, it&amp;#8217;s the same idea: the behavior of objects is not determined at compile time, it&amp;#8217;s a runtime behavior determined by a meta-object protocol. In Groovy, it translates to the fact that to each class corresponds
a meta-class which determines the behavior that an object will have when it receives a message (a method call).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This capability of doing things at runtime instead of compile time is the core of many features of dynamic languages and most of the
points illustrated in this blog post derive from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;admonitionblock note&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;icon&quot;&gt;
&lt;i class=&quot;icon-note&quot; title=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
I had some comments that the fact that dynamic languages can do OO right wasn&amp;#8217;t really interesting. In fact, I insisted on keeping this
because this is actually what makes most of the following items possible. So think of 10. as the basement for most of the following items.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_9_multimethods&quot;&gt;9. Multimethods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java supports overloaded methods. The question whether it is a good or a bad idea is beyond the scope of this post (and believe me
it is a very interesting question both in terms of semantics and performance). The idea is that an object can have two methods
of the same name accepting different parameters. Let&amp;#8217;s illustrate this with Java code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static int foo(String o) { return 1; }
public static int foo(Date o) { return 2; }
public static int foo(Object o) { return 3; }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you call it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static void main(String[] args) {
    Object[] array = new Object[] { &quot;a string&quot;, new Date(), 666 };
    for (Object o : array) {
        System.out.println(foo(o));
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think it prints? Well, most beginners will probably answer something that looks natural when you know the contents of the array:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;1
2
3&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the correct answer is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;3
3
3&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the static type of &lt;code&gt;o&lt;/code&gt; when the call to &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; is made is &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;. To say it more clearly, the declared type of &lt;code&gt;o&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt; so we are calling &lt;code&gt;foo(Object)&lt;/code&gt;. The reason for this is that the code is &lt;strong&gt;statically compiled&lt;/strong&gt; so the compiler has to know at compile time which method is going to be called. A dynamic language like Groovy chooses the method at runtime (unless, of course, you use &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic&lt;/code&gt; to enforce static semantics), so the method which is going to be called corresponds to the &lt;strong&gt;best fitting arguments&lt;/strong&gt;. So Groovy, unlike Java, will print the less surprising result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;1
2
3&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is theorically possible for a static language to do the same. But it comes at the price of performance. It would mean that the arguments have to be checked at runtime, and since static languages do not, as far as I know, implement an inlining cache, performance would be lower than those of a well designed dynamic language&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to add something to a dynamic language, what if you remove the &lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt; version of &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt;, and remove &lt;code&gt;666&lt;/code&gt; from the array? As an exercise to the reader, would this Java code compile?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public static int foo(String o) { return 1; }
public static int foo(Date o) { return 2; }

public static void main(String[] args) {
    Object[] array = new Object[] { &quot;a string&quot;, new Date() };
    for (Object o : array) {
        System.out.println(foo(o));
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, what do you have to do to make it pass? Yes, dynamic languages are superior here&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_8_duck_typing&quot;&gt;8. Duck typing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duck typing has always been a selling point of dynamic languages. Basically imagine two classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Duck {
   String getName() { &apos;Duck&apos; }
}
class Cat {
   String getName() { &apos;Cat&apos; }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those two classes define the same &lt;code&gt;getName&lt;/code&gt; method, but it is not defined explicitly in a contract (for example through an interface). There are many reasons why this can happen. For example, you didn&amp;#8217;t write those classes, they are in a third party library and for some reason those methods were not intended to be part of the contract. Imagine that you have a list of objects containing either ducks, cats, or anything else definining a &lt;code&gt;getName&lt;/code&gt; method. Then a dynamic language will let you call that method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def list = [cat, dog, human, hal]
list.each { obj -&amp;gt;
   println obj.getName()
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A static language like Java would force you to have a cast here. But since you don&amp;#8217;t have an interface defining &lt;code&gt;getName&lt;/code&gt; and implemented by all objects, you cannot cast to that type so you have to consider all types and delegate appropriately like in the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;if (obj instanceof Cat) {
   return ((Cat)obj).getName();
}
if (obj instanceof Duck) {
   return ((Duck)obj).getName();
}
if (obj instanceof Human) {
   return ((Human)obj).getName();
}
if (obj instanceof Computer) {
   return ((Computer)obj).getName();
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real solution in Java is to define either a common super class or an interface for all those, but again, sometimes you just cannot because you don&amp;#8217;t have access to the code! Imagine that the &lt;code&gt;Cat&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Dog&lt;/code&gt; classes where designed like this for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public abstract class Something {} // should define getName, but does not for some obscure reason
public class Cat extends Something {
   public String getName() { return &quot;Cat&quot;; }
}
public class Dog extends Something {
   public String getName() { return &quot;Dog&quot;; }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often the developer didn&amp;#8217;t even realize that all objects share a common interface. That&amp;#8217;s bad for you, and if you find this code you have no choice but the cascading &lt;em&gt;instanceof&lt;/em&gt; solution. There are multiple issues with that code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it is very repetitive, the only thing which changes is the type used in the test and the cast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it has to be extensive, that is to say that if your list happens to contain an object having a &lt;code&gt;getName&lt;/code&gt; method but not in your list of cases to consider, the code is broken. This means that you have to think about changing that method if you add a new type in your list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the JVM world, as the number of cases to consider grows, the size of the method will increase to the point where the JIT (just-in-time compiler) decides it&amp;#8217;s not worth inlining, potentially dramatically reducing performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, one may say &quot;but why the hell didn&amp;#8217;t you use an interface&quot;. This is of course a good way to solve this in Java, but it is not always possible. Not for example if you don&amp;#8217;t have access to the source code (think of the various classes being split in third party libraries). I often faced this problem in the past, and believe me it&amp;#8217;s no fun (I look at you, &lt;em&gt;Apache Lucene&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are actually alternatives for static languages. In Java, you could use a reflective proxy: define an interface, then create a proxy implementing that interface which will delegate to the appropriate &lt;code&gt;getName&lt;/code&gt; method. Of course it is overkill: for each object of your list you have a proxy instantiated&amp;#8230; Another option, again in Java, is to make the call reflective. But in that case, the call becomes slow and in fact, what you are doing is a dynamic call like a dynamic language would do. A language like Groovy doesn&amp;#8217;t have that problem because it implements smart techniques like call site caching and runtime bytecode generation which make it much faster than what a reflective call would do&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An elegant alternative used by other static languages is &lt;strong&gt;structural typing&lt;/strong&gt;. This is for example what the &lt;code&gt;Go&lt;/code&gt; language does. In this case, you define an interface, but the object does not have to explicitly implement the interface: the fact that the object defines a method corresponding to the method in the interface is enough to implement it. This is elegant but it changes the semantics of an interface as you define it in Java. Last but not least, this technique cannot be used on a platform like the JVM, because the virtual machine has no way to do it. Well, this is not totally true since now we have the &lt;em&gt;invokedynamic&lt;/em&gt; bytecode instruction but guess what? You are relying on a &lt;em&gt;dynamic&lt;/em&gt; feature of the VM&amp;#8230; Can you hear it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;admonitionblock note&quot;&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;icon&quot;&gt;
&lt;i class=&quot;icon-note&quot; title=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
Some argued that this is very bad design. I must repeat that if you think so, you missed the point. The idea is to &lt;strong&gt;workaround poorly designed
APIs&lt;/strong&gt; (or APIs which were &quot;optimized&quot;). When I talked about &lt;em&gt;Lucene&lt;/em&gt; it was for a very good reason. I faced the problem. &lt;em&gt;Lucene&lt;/em&gt; is a highly
optimized piece of code. It makes design decisions which are often based on performance: flattening as much as possible class hierarchies (the HotSpot
JIT doesn&amp;#8217;t like deep class hierarchies), make classes final, prefer abstract classes over interfaces, &amp;#8230; So it is easy to find classes that you want
to extend, but you can&amp;#8217;t because they are final, or classes that implicitly implement a contract but do not define interfaces. This is a pain to work
with, and the ability of a dynamic language to be able to call such methods without having to explicitly declare a contract is a real gain. Some
static languages offer similar features through structural typing, but then you have to think about what it means (virtual table lookup?) and how
it is implemented depending on the platform (on the JVM, relying on reflection is possible but you loose all type safety and have very bad performance). So everytime I used duck typing, it wasn&amp;#8217;t on APIs that &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; had designed. It was on 3rd party APIs, that for some reason didn&amp;#8217;t provide
me with a way to call some methods.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_7_respond_to_non_existing_methods&quot;&gt;7. Respond to non-existing methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dynamic language answers to messages (method calls) at runtime. This means that a well designed dynamic language should be able to let you answer &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; kind of method call, including&amp;#8230; non existing methods! This feature is at the core of powerful facilitating frameworks like Grails. In Grails, you can define a domain class like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Person {
   String firstName
   String lastName
   int age
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Person&lt;/code&gt; class does not define any method, nor does it have any explicit relation to a datastore, an ORM or SQL server. However, you can write code like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def adults = Person.findByAge { it&amp;gt;= 18 }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not dig into the details about how this is done, but the idea is to intercept the fact that the &lt;code&gt;findByAge&lt;/code&gt; method does not exist, then parse the name of the method and build a query based on the method name and the rest of the arguments (here, a closure, an open block of code). Queries can be as complex as you wish, like &lt;code&gt;findByLastNameAndAge&lt;/code&gt; or whatever you can think of. Of course Grails does some smart things here, like &lt;strong&gt;generating a new method at runtime&lt;/strong&gt;, so that the next time this method is hit, it is not an unknown method anymore, and can be invoked faster! Only a dynamic language would let you do that. Say bye to infamous DAOs that you have to change everytime you have
a new query, it is not necessary. One could say that they prefer safety at compile time rather than the ability to do this, but Grails also offers that possibility of checking that the syntax is correct at compile time, while still leveraging the dynamic runtime to make this work&amp;#8230; It&amp;#8217;s all about boilerplate removed, code verbosity and productivity&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to react to arbitrary messages is actually at the core of many DSLs (domain specific languages) written in Groovy. They are at the core of builders for example, which will let you write code like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;catalog {
   book {
   	isbn 123
	name &apos;Awesome dynamic languages&apos;
        price 11.5
        tags {
	   dynamic,
	   groovy,
	   awesome
	}
   }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the less readable Java 8 version (for the reader&amp;#8217;s mental sanity, I will not write the Java 7 version):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;builder.catalog( (el) -&amp;gt; {
  el.book ( (p) -&amp;gt; {
     p.setISBN(&quot;123&quot;);
     p.setName(&quot;Awesome dynamic languages&quot;);
     p.setPrice(11.5);
     p.setTags(&quot;dynamic&quot;,&quot;groovy&quot;,&quot;awesome&quot;);
  })
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_6_mocking_and_monkey_patching&quot;&gt;6. Mocking and monkey-patching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mocking is at the core of many unit testing strategies. Most of static languages make use of an external library to do this. Why this can be true of dynamic languages too, this is often not strictly necessary. For example Groovy offers built-in stubbing/mocking capabilities, very easily thanks to its dynamic nature. Monkey patching rely on the very same behavior but is easier to explain so I will illustrate this concept here. Imagine that you use a closed-source library (I won&amp;#8217;t judge you, I promise) or an open-source library for which you don&amp;#8217;t want to/don&amp;#8217;t have time to contribute to, but you have found a serious security issue in a method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint java language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;public class VulnerableService {
   public void vulnerableMethod() {
      FileUtils.recurseDeleteWithRootPrivileges(&quot;/&quot;);
   }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know how to fix it, but you have to wait for the maintainer to upgrade the library. Unfortunately, you can&amp;#8217;t wait because attackers are already leveraging the vulnerability on your production server (yeah, they like to). One option that a dynamic language can let you do is redefine the method at runtime. For example, in Groovy, you could write:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;VulnerableService.metaClass.vulnerableMethod = {
   println &quot;Well tried, but you have been logged to Santa&apos;s naughty guys list!&quot;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then a caller that would call the vulnerableMethod would call the monkey-patched version instead of the original one. Of course in a language like Groovy, this would only be true if the callee is dynamically compiled: if you use &lt;code&gt;@CompileStatic&lt;/code&gt; to behave like a static compiler, you&amp;#8217;re out of luck, because the method which will be invoked is selected at compile time, so you &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; be vulnerable even if you try to monkey patch&amp;#8230; Groovy provides other extension mechanisms to work around this, but it&amp;#8217;s not the topic here ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_5_dynamic_objects&quot;&gt;5. Dynamic objects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most dynamic languages let you create&amp;#8230; dynamic objects. It is basically an object for which you attach methods and properties &lt;em&gt;at runtime&lt;/em&gt;. Not that I am a big fan of it but there are some valid use cases (serialization, languages like &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/golo-lang/golo-lang/&quot;&gt;Golo&lt;/a&gt; not supporting classes, prototype based construction, &amp;#8230;). It can also be convenient if you want to rapidly prototype a class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, let&amp;#8217;s see how you could create an arbitrary object to represent a person, without actually leveraging on a class, using the Groovy language:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def p = new Expando()
p.name = &apos;Cédric&apos;
p.sayHello = { println &quot;Hello $name&quot; }

p.sayHello()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is totally dynamic here. It lets you create an arbitrary object, attach new methods to it, data, &amp;#8230;, without relying on strong typing. Of course it is interesting when you see that the &lt;code&gt;sayHello&lt;/code&gt; method is capable of referencing &quot;pseudo-fields&quot; which are themselves dynamic!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_4_scripting&quot;&gt;4. Scripting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static languages can do scripting. But it is definitely not what I would call scripting. Having to write types is not natural in a script. I even worked in the past in a context where people who wrote scripts where not programmers. They didn&amp;#8217;t even know what a type is, and they don&amp;#8217;t care. The most popular scripting technologies like Bash do not have types, and it&amp;#8217;s not a problem, so imagine the following. You arrive late at your office, your boss is very angry about that and shouts to you: &quot;you have 5 minutes, not more, to give me the total number of followers of users who have submitted an accepted pull request on the Groovy repo recently&quot;. It&amp;#8217;s a weird query, most probably your boss is going into social networking madness but you have no choice otherwise you&amp;#8217;re fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that case, most developers would think of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;using a Bash script combining &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt;, regular expressions and hoping that &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; works&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;using a tool they know like Java, but since they have so little time, they will probably rely on a regular expression to parse the JSON feed until they realize they have to do a second HTTP query for each user&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;quiting their job&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Groovy, you would do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import groovy.json.JsonSlurper

def json = new JsonSlurper().parse(&apos;https://api.github.com/repos/groovy/groovy-core/issues?state=closed&apos;.toURL())
json.user.collectEntries { u -&amp;gt;
   // second query to fetch the nb of followers
   def followers = new JsonSlurper().parse(u.followers_url.toURL())
   [u.login,followers.size()]
}.values().sum()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you can see here is that we use a facility, &lt;code&gt;JSonSlurper&lt;/code&gt; which actually parses the JSON result. It is much more reliable that what you would have done with a quick hack like a regex, but not only:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;ulist&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all data is accessible in a path-like fashion (&lt;code&gt;json.user.address.city.postalCode&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you don&amp;#8217;t need a single type here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you use a smart JSON parser with your static language, you would still have to write a collection of classes to unmarshall the JSON structure into beans/classes. For such a simple use case, you really don&amp;#8217;t care. You just want things done, easily, quickly. You don&amp;#8217;t need type safety. You don&amp;#8217;t need it to be super clean and tolerant to future changes of the JSON format. Get. Things. Done. (and boss happy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_3_runtime_coercions&quot;&gt;3. Runtime coercions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that dynamic languages are particularily good at is runtime coercions. In general static languages users know about one type of conversion, which is casting. Some are lucky enough to know about coercion (like the use of &lt;em&gt;implicit&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Scala&lt;/em&gt;), the others rely on the adapter pattern. In a dynamic language, runtime coercions are often easy to implement. A coercion differs from a cast in the sense that you want to convert an object of &lt;code&gt;class A&lt;/code&gt; to an object of &lt;code&gt;class B&lt;/code&gt;, but a &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; cannot be assigned to an &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groovy provides &quot;natural&quot; conversions for some widely used types: lists to objects, and maps to object, like in the example here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Point p = [1,2] // coercion of a list literal into an object of class Point thanks to constructor injection
Point p = [x:1, y:2] // coercion of a map literal into an object of class Point thanks to setter injection&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if it happened to be that you cannot use maps or lists but really want to convert one type to another, you can just declare a converter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class A {
   Object asType(Class&amp;lt;?&amp;gt; clazz) { new B(...) }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can see you raising an eyebrow here, because I wrote the conversion code directly in class &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;, but remember it&amp;#8217;s a dynamic language with a meta-object protocol, so nothing prevents you from writing this conversion code &lt;strong&gt;outside&lt;/strong&gt; of the class &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; itself, through its metaclass, which would let you add conversion algorithms for classes which are beyond your control. It&amp;#8217;s a win!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_2_dynamic_binding&quot;&gt;2. Dynamic binding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic binding is linked to DSL evaluation and scripting. Imagine the following script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;listingblock&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint groovy language-groovy&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;a+b&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this script, variables &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; are &lt;code&gt;unbound&lt;/code&gt;. They are not known from a compiler, so if you tried to statically compile this with a compiler like &lt;em&gt;Java&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;C++&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Scala&lt;/em&gt;) it would definitely blow up. Not if you compile this with &lt;em&gt;Groovy&lt;/em&gt;. Because it&amp;#8217;s dynamic, it&amp;#8217;s able to know that those variables &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; be eventually bound, when the script is executed. Groovy provides means to &lt;em&gt;inject&lt;/em&gt; those variables when you need them. It is some kind of late binding, but it is the core of expression languages, and it is no surprise that products like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/1.4/modules-scripting.html#modules-scripting&quot;&gt;ElasticSearch&lt;/a&gt; uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/1.4/modules-scripting.html#modules-scripting&quot;&gt;Groovy as the default scripting language&lt;/a&gt;: it allows it to be both compilable and late bound. But there is more, if you think you have an issue with not being able to resolve &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; at compile time and that you fear to write code which might fail at runtime&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sect1&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;_1_mixed_mode_compilation&quot;&gt;1. Mixed mode compilation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;sectionbody&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last thing that a dynamic language like Groovy is capable of doing is leveraging &lt;strong&gt;mixed mode&lt;/strong&gt; compilation. Behind this curious term is a unique concept in programming languages: Groovy is able of mixing static code with dynamic code, but more, you can instruct the compiler how to do so. So if you design a DSL like in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/1.4/modules-scripting.html#modules-scripting&quot;&gt;ElasticSearch&lt;/a&gt; where you know that some variables will be bound, that the number, names and &lt;strong&gt;types&lt;/strong&gt; of those variables are fixed and known in advance, then you can instruct the compiler and switch to a statically compilable mode! This means that if the user uses an unknown variable, compilation will fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique is already used in Groovy itself, in the powerful &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.groovy-lang.org/latest/html/documentation/markup-template-engine.html&quot;&gt;Markup Template Engine&lt;/a&gt;. It is a template engine which is capable of generating markup-like contents with a very nice builder-like syntax, but all templates are statically compiled even if the code seems to be full of unresolved method calls or variables!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who are interested in this, I invite them to take an eye at my &lt;a href=&quot;http://melix.github.io/blog/2014/02/markuptemplateengine.html&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; describing how you can do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;_conclusion&quot; class=&quot;sect0&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I have highlighted some points where dynamic languages can do what static languages cannot. Users of the most widely used dynamic language, Javascript, probably have lots of ideas too. The point for me is &lt;strong&gt;not to tell which one is better than the other&lt;/strong&gt; because &lt;strong&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t care&lt;/strong&gt;. In general, I am not much into the war behind those, because I really enjoy both. I do static typing most of time, but I really enjoy the dynamic nature of the language too because often I don&amp;#8217;t want to be slowed down just to make a compiler happy. I, as a developer, should be happy. Making a compiler happy is secondary and often not necessary. Last but not least, you might have thought, reading this post, that &lt;strong&gt;your&lt;/strong&gt; static language can do this or that. I won&amp;#8217;t blame you here, because mine can too. The idea here is more to show that it is totally unnatural for a static language or it often comes with horrible drawbacks like verbosity, performance issues or simply difficult to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what about using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.groovy-lang.org&quot;&gt;language that brings the best of the two worlds together&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
	</description>
    </item>

  </channel> 
</rss>
